<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disputation between a doctor and an apothecary, or, A reply to the new argument of Dr. R. Burthogge, M.D. for infants baptism wherein the novelty in which it glories is justly censured and its harmony proved to be no better than self repugnancy and a manifest abuse of scripture / by Philip Cary, a neighbouring apothecary ...</title>
            <author>Cary, Philip.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C740</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875282</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50193</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50193)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 997:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disputation between a doctor and an apothecary, or, A reply to the new argument of Dr. R. Burthogge, M.D. for infants baptism wherein the novelty in which it glories is justly censured and its harmony proved to be no better than self repugnancy and a manifest abuse of scripture / by Philip Cary, a neighbouring apothecary ...</title>
                  <author>Cary, Philip.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.W. for the author and are to be sold by R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burthogge, Richard, 1638?-ca. 1700.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50193:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50193:1"/>
            <p>A DISPUTATION Between a DOCTOR And an <hi>Apothecary:</hi> OR A REPLY to the NEW ARGU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT of Dr. <hi>R. Burthogge,</hi> M. D. FOR <hi>Infants Baptiſm;</hi> Wherein the Novelty in which it glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, is juſtly cenſured, and its Harmony proved to be no better than ſelf Repugnancy, and a manifeſt abuſe of Scripture.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Philip Cary,</hi> a neighbouring Apothecary, a lover of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 18. 17.</bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe, ſeemeth juſt; but his <hi>Neighbour</hi> cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. W.</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Baldwin.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50193:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50193:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Am ſenſible my Title page needs an Epiſtle Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, leſt it ſhould ſeem either Romantick, or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous. But let it not be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as imprudent in this learned Doctor to meaſure Weapons with an unskilful Apothecary; nor preſumptuous in me to enter the Liſts, and draw my ſhort Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon this Learned Man. It is true, the Doctor with whom I
<pb facs="tcp:50193:3"/> combate, is of a ſingular acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, commanding eloquence, and great prudence: But yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, it may not ſeem any more a ſlide or errour in his prudentials in chuſing me for his Antagoniſt, who am every way ſo much his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior, than it was a defect in that rare Limner's skill, who to give the Picture of the late Queen a comparative addition of ſtature, drew her Dwarf by her ſide, booted, ſpurred, and ſworded, with her Hand ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to reach the crown of his Head. Which being duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, you will have the leſs reaſon to cenſure the Doctor as impolitick in his choice of ſuch an one as I am, to be his Combatant. But yet leſt the diſparity ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:50193:3"/> ſeem too great, he hath thought fit however to tell the Reader in p. 18. of his Epiſtle, <q rend="inline">That he does not apprehend it any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace (as ſome would have it) to have been ingaged with me; for that I am a careful, painful, and induſtrious ſearching perſon, much converſant in the preſent Controverſie; and (as he believes) can ſay as much for my Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as any other whatſoever.</q> So that I hope, enough is ſaid in a few words, to ſalve the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Adverſaries prudence in <hi>his</hi> choice.</p>
            <p>A Word or two more is but neceſſary to obviate thy cenſure of my preſumption in entring the Liſts with this Learned Man, whoſe ſame hath more than once
<pb facs="tcp:50193:4"/> been reſounded from the Preſs. And all that I have to ſay for my ſelf is this, It was not choice but neceſſity that hath drawn me in. I was attacked by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor with this New Argument, both in Front, Flank, and Rear, with ſo much briskneſs in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Diſpute; that I confeſs I was quite overborn, as well with the ſurprizing novelty of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as with the rapid ſtream of his irreſiſtable eloquence; leaving him a fair Field: So that it was with me for ſome time, as with the ſilly Froggs in the Fable; who were all ſtruck into ſilence and amazement, by the Log thrown down by <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> among them; till at laſt not perceiving it move, they craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:50193:4"/> nearer to it, and perceiving it to be a ſenſeleſs thing which had ſo affrighted them; they grew bold enough to hop without fear upon it, and over it, and round about it. Thus it fared with me, who ſtood a while like a man aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, at this uncouth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but coming nearer to it, I found it as meer a Log, as that was: and not caſt only at me, but at all thoſe that are the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates and Aſſerters of Infants Baptiſm alſo: (all others, but himſelf, as he affirms, hanging it on Wyres, or by Geometry only:) Upon this I rouzed up my cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; and having undertook the Doctor in ſeveral private Letters that had paſt to and fro betwixt us; though I never thought to
<pb facs="tcp:50193:5"/> have made the matter more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; yet the Doctor having been pleaſed to print his own Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that by themſelves, I am thereby neceſſitated as well as incouraged, to follow and attend his motions, according to the duty of my place.</p>
            <p>If I ſeem to be defective in that deference I owe him, or too ſmart in any part of my reply, I beſeech thee before I come under thy cenſure, to read thoſe paſſages in the Doctor which gave the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; and ſee whether my words be above the value of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking cauſe? If thou be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and equal Judge, I dare refer my ſelf wholly to thee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Doctor hath not with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual abſurdity, in the Book I
<pb facs="tcp:50193:5"/> here deal with, made <hi>Abraham</hi> the Repreſentative of the Carnal Seed, included Baptiſm in the 17. of <hi>Gen.</hi> and excluded the firſt and grand Covenant-Promiſe out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 'Tis to me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing that ſo clear and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing an Eye ſhould ſee a Command for Infants Baptiſm in Gen. 17. and not to be able to diſcern the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace in <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. his notion concerning the latter of which, you will find p. 110. of his preſent Diſcourſe; where he is pleaſed to tell me, <q rend="inline">That the Words in the laſt mentioned Scripture, were not told (as I had expreſſed it) to <hi>Adam,</hi> but to the Serpent, as being ſpoken not by way of Promiſe to the one, but of denunciation of
<pb facs="tcp:50193:6"/> a Sentence on the other;</q> with much more to the ſame purpoſe: the introduction whereof you will find at p. 99.</p>
            <p>If I ſeem to be concerned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the rate of my ordinary tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, (the caſe ſtanding as it doth) it is zeal for the abuſed Word of God that hath warmed me. I am conſcious of no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice toward the perſon of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; neither do I love to draw the Saw of contention with any man, much leſs with one that is ſo much my ſuperior: But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity will make Cowards fight. Neceſſity (as the Doctor well knows) will make a man do greater things than this: It will at leaſt excuſe me from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in reſpect of the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.
<pb facs="tcp:50193:6"/> But it is very probable, the Doctor may meet with rougher hands than mine in this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; all ſorts of perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerned in it, as that which bears hard upon them, and is like accordingly to be reſented by them. I honour his perſon, whilſt I detect and cenſure his errours, and abuſes of the Scriptures. I daily pray for the deſirable unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace; and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all Chriſtian Service and Affection, <hi>Philip Cary.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="disputation">
            <pb facs="tcp:50193:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50193:7"/>
            <head>Animadverſions, and Reflections, upon a late Diſcourſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and Learned Dr. <hi>Richard Burthogge,</hi> M. D. againſt a neighbouring Apothecary, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled as followeth,</head>
            <div type="discourse">
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <q rend="inline">AN Argument for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm, dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Faith, and Harmony of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. In which in a method wholly New, and upon Grounds not commonly obſerved, both the Doctrine (of Infants Baptiſm) is fully aſſerted, and the Objections againſt it are obviated.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50193:8"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> 
                  <hi>Analogy</hi> and <hi>Harmony</hi> are Words of a taking ſound, and delicious Air, melodiouſly chiming in the Readers attention. But it is not very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that that Diſcourſe ſhould deſerve ſo pompous a title, which abounds with ſelf repugnancies, and contradictions. To give the Reader a taſte, and but a taſte of this harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Diſcourſe. In his Epiſtle to the Reader, p. 18. he ſaith. <q rend="inline">The Point in controverſy is not a point of human learning: Here (for the main) is no need of Greek, or Hebrew, or of the ſubtleties of the Schoolmen, or of <hi>exactneſs of Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm.</hi>
                  </q> Analogically and Harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally whereunto he delivers himſelf, and that upon the main Point, and very Hinge of the Controverſy in theſe Words, <hi>p.</hi> 88. <q rend="inline">If you ſay I am too <hi>Critical;</hi> I ſay, this is a Text that muſt be underſtood <hi>Critically.</hi> The Apoſtle was as <hi>critical</hi> upon it as I, or any Man can be, when he obſerved, it is ſaid <hi>Seed,</hi> as ſpeaking of one, and not <hi>Seeds;</hi> and what he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50193:8"/> ſaith, is the proper Key to unlock the Text.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In his Epiſtle, <hi>p.</hi> 5. he tells us, <q rend="inline">He was concerned to ſee an Article of that importance, as Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is, to hang on <hi>Wyres</hi> only, and by <hi>Geometry.</hi> And that he could not ſee it owner of <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>ſolid</hi> foundations, unleſs it be as he here layes it.</q> Harmonical with which (if that be to Harmonize) is what he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 79. <q rend="inline">Where he high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applauds Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as abundantly proving the Church Memberſhip of Infants.</q> The <hi>Wyres</hi> then on which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hang'd it, were it ſeems a <hi>ſolid</hi> Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or elſe an <hi>abundant proof</hi> is none.</p>
               <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 122. <q rend="inline">He calls my Opinion, an upſtart Opinion, or Novelty; not of above an Age or Century.</q> In Harmony wherewith if that be ſo, he ſaith to this purpoſe, <hi>p.</hi> 74. <q rend="inline">That 'tis probable thoſe that would not ſuffer little Children to come to Chriſt, were of <hi>my Perſwaſion.</hi>
                  </q> If ſo, my Opinion, according to the Doctors own Conceſſion, is no late, upſtart opinion.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50193:9"/>
               <p>Having done with the <hi>Harmony;</hi> I ſhall next reflect upon the <hi>Novelty</hi> of the Doctor's Argument. <q rend="inline">Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>in a Method wholly new.</hi>
                  </q> New, and wholly New, are Charms as powerful, as <hi>Analogy</hi> and <hi>Harmony.</hi> 'Tis the nature of Man, ſaith <hi>Seneca, magis nova quam magna mirari,</hi> to admire things <hi>new,</hi> rather than <hi>great</hi> and <hi>worthy,</hi> But I muſt tell you, Doctor, that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators</hi> hear not well among the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious. And that of all Men you ſhould not ſcoff at <hi>New-light,</hi> as you do without cauſe in many parts of your Diſcourſe. You have bleſſed the World with a new Light, if your Argument have as much of weight, as your Title Page and Epiſtles have of Pomp and Oſtentation. A Light which will alter many receive Schemes, as you ſay, Epiſtle, <hi>p.</hi> 19. But how alter many? why not all? If your Argument be <hi>wholly new,</hi> and the Doctrine of Infants Baptiſm hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before but upon <hi>Wyres,</hi> and by <hi>Geometry,</hi> as you ſay; it muſt alter <hi>All</hi> the former Schemes. And this being the <hi>only ſolid</hi> Foundation, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters them <hi>deſervedly.</hi> For why ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50193:9"/> ſo great an Article as Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm hang any longer by <hi>Geometry,</hi> as <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Tomb at <hi>Mecca</hi> is ſaid to do? When you have laid a <hi>ſolid</hi> Foundation for it, 'tis fit it ſhould ſtand upon its <hi>own Baſis</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>This is a bold attempt, a brave Word for the Cauſe you mannage; brave indeed, if it ſucceed well, and that you convince the learned World by it, That all former Aſſertors and Champions of Infant Baptiſm did but <hi>Wyre-draw</hi> the Scriptures, and hanged all by <hi>Geometry.</hi> But I muſt here mind you, That the <hi>Licians</hi> ſuffered none to propoſe a new Law, but at his own peril; that if the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof were not approved, he that offered it might pay for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. The Church of <hi>England,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>all</hi> the Advocates and Aſſerters of Infants Baptiſm, are more concerned in this paſſage than my ſelf. Let them look to the <hi>old Foundations,</hi> I am principally (at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at leaſt) concerned about this <hi>New one;</hi> wherein I fight, and indeed can fight againſt no other Party, or Perſon in the World but Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogge;</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50193:10"/> ſeeing I now oppoſe that which no man ever urged, or aſſerted beſide, or before himſelf; which is a good Breaſt-work for my ſecurity againſt all other adverſaries. Indeed you have choſen a <hi>New ground</hi> to fight upon, not ſo much with ſuch a Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron as I am; but all the learned that will ſtand by their <hi>old Arguments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, Sir, you have ſtrawed the Readers way with flowers of Rhetorick, and charmed his ears with melodious ſounds, <hi>New</hi> and <hi>wholly New;</hi> and <hi>not commonly obſerved.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this is every mans Money; and I am confident would be ſo, if your Book-ſeller Mr. <hi>Jonathan Greenwood</hi>'s Shop at the Crown in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> did but ſtand over againſt the <hi>New-Exchange</hi> at <hi>Athens;</hi> if it be not <hi>New,</hi> none will regard it: and if not <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly New,</hi> ſome body would ſhare ſtakes with you, when you come to divide the ſpoils in the Field of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. And Social glory is but an half-Mooned honour. All or None is the game for him that aſpires to the reputation of a Non-ſuch.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50193:10"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> p. 5</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">The Argument I go upon, as I do mannage it, is not common; and hath little Authority to make it good, beſide that of ſound Reaſon, good Senſe, and Scripture Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> That it is not common, as you do mannage it, is undeniable: And that it hath little Authority to make it good, beſides ſound Reaſon, good Senſe, and Scripture Harmony; you voluntarily confeſs: And indeed if it have theſe three Vouchers, it hath enough. I value not other Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that ſhall come after theſe, more than ſupernumeraries, or a caſt upon the full meaſure, <hi>ex abundanti.</hi> But then your three Vouchers muſt ſpeak home to the point in plain and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible words: for ſhould theſe fail you too (as I am much of the mind they will) you are then by your own acknowledgment, left utterly alone. And <hi>Wo to him</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>that</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50193:11"/> 
                  <hi>is alone:</hi> Thoſe that err with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of learned and grave Men, will ſcape better in the crowd, than he that ſtands ſingle and naked, as you do.</p>
               <p>But, Sir, if your Argument be wholly <hi>New,</hi> and the only <hi>ſolid</hi> Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the great Article of Infants Baptiſm; all others hanging it upon <hi>Wyres,</hi> and by <hi>Geometry,</hi> as you ſpeak; And that yours be (as here you add) ſupported by ſound Reaſons, good Senſe, and Scripture Harmony: ſuch a poor ſmatterer in Logick as I am, would be apt to inferr, That certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the old Schemes which it alters, muſt needs be irrational, nonſenſical, and confuſed: For I ſhould think, ſound Reaſon removes, or alters no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is ſo far irrational, as it alters it; and good Senſe nothing but what is Nonſenſical; nor Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony any thing but what is confuſed and jarring: For my Natural Logick teacheth me that Senſe fights not with Senſe, but Nonſenſe; Reaſon oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not Reaſon, but what is Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; and Harmony nothing but Confuſion and Diſorder. And veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Sir, 'tis matter of admiration to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50193:11"/> me, and I believe will be ſo to your Readers, how all the Senſe, Reaſon and Harmony came to be center'd within the compaſs of <hi>your Pericrani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> and that in ſo ſearching and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical an Age, and in ſo celebrated, and long bandied a Controverſie as this, no Man ſhould be ſo fortunate, to light upon the ſolid grounds of ſound Reaſon, good Senſe, and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Harmony, before or beſides your ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtle.</hi> &amp;c. p. 5.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">To the Queſtion, How I came to hit upon it?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> You have ſeaſonably anticipated me, I was juſt going to put the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, What benevolent, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious Star guided you to this New Diſcovery? We know that little cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are noted by <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> as moſt memorable and famous things, by which the renowned Adventurers, ſuch as <hi>Columbus, Drake, &amp;c.</hi> were firſt guided to, or incouraged in their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50193:12"/> New Diſcoveries. You may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well imagine (as you here do) that upon your firſt diſcovery of this <hi>Terra Nova,</hi> all the amazed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring crowd would ſoon ſurround you, and even tire you with this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>How you came to hit upon it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How you did I do not know; for my part I have viewed the Text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. where your New Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very is ſaid to be, with the beſt Eyes I have, and can ſee nothing more than what the old, ſolid Interpreters (that travel'd and ſearcht that ſpot, before you or I were born) have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſcovered. And I am ſure they tell us of no ſuch Senſe as yours; no not a Man of them, as your ſelf confeſs. It is juſtly therefore a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to me, <hi>How you came to hit upon it?</hi> and it was very ſeaſonable to put it in the place where you did: for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, it is a Queſtion hanging by <hi>Geometry</hi> upon the lip of every man that reads you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaac</hi> asked <hi>Jacob</hi> juſt ſuch another Queſtion, concerning his Veniſon: <hi>How cameſt thou by it ſo ſoon my Son?</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>the Lord brought it to me.</hi> 'Tis like there is as much ſincerity in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50193:12"/> your Anſwer, as in <hi>Jacob</hi>'s: And I believe there is. You inſinuate that you were concerned to ſee ſuch an Article as Infant-Baptiſm hang but upon <hi>Wyres,</hi> and therefore ſought for a better; and at laſt found it, or dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it out of the Quarry of ſound Reaſon, good Senſe, and Scripture Harmony; and ſo challenge the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the firſt Diſcoverer: <hi>Ego pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inveni,</hi> is no common badge of honour in my opinion; it is no great matter who firſt found it, but whether it be worth the finding.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> p. 17.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">I take it to have been a piece of vanity in him (ſpeaking of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent adverſary) to tell me as he doth (that, as he remembred, one of the Schoolmen ſaid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Becauſe I have reaſon to believe he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the Schoolmen, as little as Greek or Hebrew.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> The paſſage I referred to in the Schoolmen, is very intelligible by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50193:13"/> any man that was never skilled in the learned Languages, as well as by your ſelf; whoſe skill I hope is greater in the Tongues, than it appears to be in the interpretation of Scriptures. They ſay, <hi>That if the Workmans hand were his Rule, he could never err in working:</hi> I applyed it by ſaying, That if your Gloſſes and Interpretations be as authentick as the Text, you can never err in the Interpretation: Did this grate? I fear many paſſages will grate more (though in none I deſign your exaſperation) before you and I have ended. Did I deſerve to be called <hi>John Duns</hi> his Scholar for this? I had it not from <hi>John Duns</hi> (alias <hi>Scotus:</hi>) though if I had, I may as well ſay, He was a dunce without <hi>dulneſs;</hi> as one ſomewhere calls <hi>Naaman</hi>'s ſin, a ſin without <hi>guilt.</hi> It is not the firſt time a pleaſant fancy hath ſported with the name of <hi>John Duns;</hi> nor the firſt time it hath been well repayed for ſuch wanton ſport. This ſubtle Doctor was once ſitting at Table with <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>bald,</hi> Emperor and King of <hi>France;</hi> and behaving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a little ruſtically and homely, as I do with you, the Emperor jeſtingly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50193:13"/> asked him, <hi>Quid intereſt inter Scotum &amp; Sotum?</hi> What is between a <hi>Scot</hi> and a Sot? He Anſwered, <hi>Menſa,</hi> the Table. I dare not be ſo vain to ſay turn the Table with the ſtory: no, no; I acknowledge you a man of parts; every way my ſuperior; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not worthy the name of <hi>John Duns</hi> or Dr. <hi>Burthogge</hi>'s Scholar: But you ſee the greateſt men, even Emperors, as well as your ſelf, cannot ſo ſport with impunity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> You conclude to the Reader thus; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> p. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q rend="inline">That you are much confirmed in the Grounds you have laid as to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of them, by their undergoing <hi>one</hi> kind of <hi>Teſt,</hi> without any loſs; yet before you advance them from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing points of meer <hi>Opinion,</hi> to be points of ſome degree of <hi>Faith,</hi> you are willing they ſhould undergo <hi>all others.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> 'Tis unaccountable how ſo learned, acute, and perſpicacious a man as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50193:14"/> you, who have altered all Schemes that the learned of the Age have drawn, in reference to Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and adventured to call them <hi>Wyres,</hi> and <hi>Geometry,</hi> ſhould be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> from ſuch an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate, ſoft-headed Dunce, as you repreſent me in theſe your Letters to be. What can I add to you? but to be <hi>confirmed:</hi> Ai, and <hi>much confirmed</hi> in thoſe your very <hi>Grounds,</hi> by their undergoing <hi>my Teſt;</hi> ſeems to be not only a <hi>plaiſter</hi> to heal my ſoft pate, which you have often broken; but ſuch a <hi>Crown</hi> put upon it as I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to wear.</p>
               <p>But whether your Dictates have paſſed <hi>my Teſt</hi> without <hi>any loſs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs properly to the Reader to judge. 'Tis poſſible he may think you have loſt your deſign, your own, and his underſtanding too, if he have but patience to trace you through your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, involved, and myſtical inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations and Paraphraſes.</p>
               <p>However this is a commendable ſtrain of modeſty; <q rend="inline">That before you advance them from being Points of meer Opinion, to be Points of ſome degree of Faith, you are willing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50193:14"/> they ſhould undergo all others.</q> It ſeems then, all that you have ſo confidently argued for, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in theſe Letters, is not yet in the leaſt degree a Point of your <hi>Faith,</hi> but meer opinion. That's modeſtly inſinuated, like a Man conſcious of his liableneſs to miſtakes; and that his <hi>own</hi> Argument may hang upon <hi>Wyres,</hi> and by <hi>Geometry,</hi> as well as <hi>other mens:</hi> But then I am ſtumbled as much at the back-door of your Epiſtle, as I was at the fore-door of your gawdy Title page; for I muſt ingenuouſly acknowledge, I do not underſtand, How the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or approbation of your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, is capable to advance your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, from being a meer Opinion to ſome degree of Faith: for ſhould they all approve, and applaud it; (which I am perſwaded few will do) yet when all is done; your Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying upon <hi>humane</hi> Grounds, could be advanced no higher than to a <hi>humane</hi> Faith: except you ultimately reſolve it into your Readers Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Papiſts do theirs into that of the Church.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50193:15"/>
               <p>And thus much for your ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Title page, and charming Epiſtle; I now come to your Letters; the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion whereof you thus hint at, and but hint, in your firſt page.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Dear Sir,</hi> I cannot believe my ſelf obliged by the occaſional Diſcourſe (which I held almoſt a year and three quarters agoe) about Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, to engage any further in that controverſie.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> It would ſcarce be worth the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders time to be informed of the nativity of this Controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, were it not to undeceive him, if he take me (as who that reads your Letter but would) for the firſt aggreſſor: I will be ſhort and plain. The occaſion was thus, A Gentleman in the Neighbourhood lying ſick, the Doctor was ſent for to adminiſter to him; and I was then
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50193:15"/> alſo obliged to attend him; The Doctor being an active, diſcurſive perſon, was pleaſed, if not for pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, yet at leaſt to gratifie the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany (amongſt which the Lady to whom he dedicates it, was one of the chief) to provoke me to diſpute the point of Infant Baptiſm with him: I declined ſeveral times the Ladyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, in that reſpect; though the Doctor was ready, as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my diſtance, and inſufficiency to cope with ſo acute and learned a perſon; but all would not do, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute I muſt, and being unawares for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into the liſts, a new Argument never drawn before in this field of Controverſie, was now drawn, and brandiſht formidably againſt me, till at laſt I was overthrown, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inſulted over as a vanquiſhed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; my Sword being as it were broken over my head with great triumph.</p>
               <p>I bore theſe inſults as well as I could: but the Reader may eaſily imagine the anguiſh I was in, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering ſo many ſpectators preſent as there were. If I had not been ſo much confounded as I was,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50193:16"/> I might then have told him as I did afterward; That as it was no diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to <hi>Melancthon,</hi> ſo neither can it be to any that diſputes for truth, not victory, to anſwer as he did to <hi>Eckius, Cras tibi reſpondebo.</hi> However, though I had no intention to have appeared in my own vindication, againſt a man ſo much my ſuperior in place and parts; yet when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered how the truth which I profeſs lay at ſtake, (though I had almoſt loſt the ſenſe of the Doctors Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I did after ſome time give him a Letter; which occaſioned his firſt Letter to me, by way of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, wherein the Grounds he goes upon are laid down, and which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he proceeds to illuſtrate in his following Letters; which being now made publick, I judge my ſelf under a neceſſity, to publiſh the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of thoſe Letters of mine, which I have ſent unto him alſo, upon that ſubject, that the Reader may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be enabled to paſs his judgment upon the ſtate of the Controverſie between us; which I ſuppoſe could not but prudently have been ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, upon a partial Information only.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50193:16"/>
               <p>In order hereunto, I have thought it neceſſary, to draw up the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scheme of what hath paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Doctor and my ſelf, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the principal Argument in diſpute between us; the thread whereof might not otherwiſe have been ſo clearly diſcerned, through the interpoſure of divers other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercurring paſſages, in the ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that have paſſed between us. After therefore I had diſpatcht my firſt Letter to him; in his Reply (cutting off what is ſuperfluous and not to the point) he was pleaſed thus to beſpeak me:</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> Though I cannot believe my ſelf obliged by the occaſional Diſcourſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Doctors new Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Infants-Baptiſm,</hi> p. 1, 2, 3, 7, 8, 52, 53.</note> (which I held about a year and three quarters ago) about Infants Baptiſm, to engage further, and that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately too in that Controverſie; yet having received from you ſo large and ſo elaborate an endeavour for my ſatisfaction, — I may not be ſo much wanting, either in civility to your deſires, or in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50193:17"/> to the call that I believe in them, as to decline the incumbence and obligation they put me under to anſwer: and ſo either to receive my ſelf a further illumination in the Point before us, or (which is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and which I hope) to give it.</p>
               <p>As for my ſentiments on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, without concerning of my ſelf in other Arguments inſiſted on by others, and alſo touched and reflected on by you, I will immediately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to diſplay and lay out the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for Paedobaptiſm, as it is founded on the Covenant or Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in all its force and evidence; and to do it to ſome purpoſe, I will demonſtrate,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the Covenant of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> which is called <hi>the Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham, <hi>or the Promiſe of the Spirit,</hi> is ſtill in force, and is that Covenant of Grace the true believing Gentiles are under.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That in reſpect of that Covenant of Promiſe, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the bleſſing of Abraham, and the promiſe of the Spirit;</hi> all the ſeed that hath the benefit of it, are under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual obligations to the duty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50193:17"/> ariſing from it, that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was himſelf.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I will ſhew that the duty and incumbence, ariſing from that Covenant or Bleſſing, to which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was obliged; was by way of reſtipulation, to dedicate and give himſelf, and all that was his, to God; and in token of that dedication of himſelf, and all that was his to God, to wear himſelf the ſign of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; and to put it as a cogniſance, and badge, and mark of God upon all that were his, and were capable of it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, I will alſo ſhew that from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s dedication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all his to God, there ariſes a diſtinction of holineſs, into inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and external; abſolute and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and that this diſtinction of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is Evangelical.</p>
               <p>From all which it will follow; That the true believing Gentiles, which are the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and as much partakers of the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> as himſelf, are as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to keep that Covenant of Promiſe, in the ſign and token of it, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and his natural Seed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50193:18"/> were: that is, in token of the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of themſelves, and all that is theirs; every Father of a Family is to take the ſign of God upon himſelf, and to put it upon all is his, and capable of it; and to be ſure our Children are ours: And ſince circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is no longer that ſign, but Baptiſm is; it is the duty of every Father and Mother of the Family, both to be baptized themſelves, and to ſee that all that are theirs, their own, their property, under their dominion, and at their diſpoſe be ſo. And I think as it is a duty in the Parent, or Father of the Family to give; ſo it is a priviledge in thoſe that are ſo, to be given to God, and to have his ſign upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> 
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> I have received yours, and ſhall immediately proceed to conſider and give anſwer to the Argument for Paedobaptiſm, founded on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as it is now repreſented and inſiſted on by you. And as to the four Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50193:18"/> on which your concluſion is founded; I muſt beg your patience to ſee that frame of Argument, which you have ſo ſtrongly built and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, diſſolved in theſe following di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions I have made upon them; and conſequently your whole Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment falling with it.</p>
               <p>In your firſt Propoſition I only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Spiritual eſſence of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to deſcend upon believing Gentiles: but that the additaments, and appendages, being variable things, and ſeparable from it, do not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily deſcend with it. As I have elſewhere, at large, evinced unto you.</p>
               <p>In your ſecond Propoſition, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the Seed of believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles that have the benefit of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, and to whom it is made, are under an equal obligation unto thoſe proper duties and ſervices now required of them, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was himſelf; underſtanding it of the adult believing off-ſpring, and not the infant Seed of believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50193:19"/>
               <p>In your third Propoſition, I allow that the believing Gentiles are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to dedicate themſelves, and all that is theirs to God, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was. But inaſmuch as there is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dedication; the one by Baptiſm; and the other by religious Education and fervent ſupplication: this latter dedication I allow: the former, as it reſpects our infant Seed, for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I have elſwhere given you, I deny.</p>
               <p>In your fourth Propoſition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a two-fold Holineſs, Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Internal; abſolute and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, ariſing from the Covenant: though I grant that ſo it was under the former Adminiſtration; yet I have elſewhere proved, that as for any External or Relative Holineſs then ariſing from the Covenant, it is now aboliſhed. And as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready alſo demonſtrated that the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. doth not at all prove the continuation thereof in the Goſpel day; ſo neither is there any other Scripture, that I know of, that can be pertinently alledged for the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of ſuch a notion: though I grant that there is an external and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50193:19"/> internal holineſs now ariſing among Gentile Profeſſors: the latter from the Covenant; the former from a meer pretenſion to it.</p>
               <p>In theſe four Propoſitions lies the main ſtrength of your New Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Infants Baptiſm. And <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. where the Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is recorded, is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Text you bottom upon; the grounds of Infant Baptiſm, according to you, being to be found there, or no where. That they are not to be found there, will appear, I ſuppoſe, in the iſſue. That they are not to be found in the New Teſtament, your ſelf have confeſſed to me in theſe words of your firſt Letter, <hi>p.</hi> 62. where you tell me, <q rend="inline">That we are not to expect any New Commands in the Goſpel Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for duties ſettled of old, on laſting and immutable Reaſons;</q> and more expreſly, you tell the Reader in your Epiſtle, <hi>p.</hi> 10. <q rend="inline">That in the New Teſtament, no new Rule is given either by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, or by his Apoſtles and Followers, about the ſubjects of the ſign of the Covenant, which ſign now is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. And therefore certainly (ſay
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50193:20"/> you) it leaves us to the Grounds and Reaſons of the Old Teſtament.</q> Now I ſuppoſe, your ſelf and all will grant that if a Rule for Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is not to be found in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. it is not to be found in any <hi>other</hi> Old Teſtament Text. And if it be to be found in that Text; it is incumbent on you who aſſert it, to prove, Firſt, your three parties in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant there mentioned. Secondly, your two Signs. Thirdly, that <hi>Abraham</hi> repreſented the carnal Seed only, in Circumciſion; and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Spiritual Seed in Baptiſm; though himſelf the Head and Figure of Gentile Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, was never baptized, nor the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſm inſtituted for many hundred years after his death. Your proofs for all theſe Aſſertions, or rather ungrounded hypotheſes, come in order to be conſidered, after I have traced your more general diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>At preſent all I ſhall ſay is only this; That it is apparent unto me at leaſt, that there is an abſolute neceſſity to keep cloſe unto <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Commands about <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> Worſhip; that Text in <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> you inſiſt on, (as far as my Eyes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50193:20"/> do ſerve me) having no fellowſhip with the preſent Argument, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency to evince the Juſtice of the preſent practice. And therefore though it may be good to argue thus; It is Gods mind, therefore it is to be done; yet it is too much for us to argue, this ſhould be, and therefore God hath appointed it; inaſmuch as no Reaſon of ours in poſitive Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſuch as Baptiſm is, but Gods will alone, gathered by ſome expreſs command or example in the New Teſtament, can acquit an action ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed from the guilt of Will-worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 54.</note> If I thought it could be denied that Baptiſm is the ſign of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, I ſhould think it eaſie to evince it: But I take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Baptiſm is now, as Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was the ſign of the Covenant in the Evangelical Adminiſtration, becauſe it is the Reſtipulation, and Anſwer of a good Conſcience to God. And becauſe it hath the ſame uſe now that Circumciſion had, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50193:21"/> to be the right of Matriculation and our Aſſignation. And becauſe elſe (which is hard to think) there is now no ſuch Sign and Token of the Covenant; whereas if in Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (Gods ſign) in Baptiſm the name of God is put upon us to mark us for his. And taking it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and allowing the Grounds which I have laid; you may ſee the Reaſon why in the Primitive times whole Houſes were baptized? it is on the ſame account, and for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s whole Houſe was Circumciſed. Thus it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. 14. that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould tell <hi>Cornelius</hi> words, <hi>by which he and all his Houſe ſhould be ſaved.</hi> And <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 15. it is ſaid, but of <hi>Lydia,</hi> That ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved: but of her and her Houſhold, that they were baptized. And <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 31. It is promiſed to the Gaoler, That on his Faith, not only himſelf but his Houſhold ſhould be ſaved. <hi>Believe thou on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That this laſt paſſage is now left out in the printed co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the Doctors firſt Letter: though he was pleaſed thus to expreſs himſelf in the firſt edition of that Letter to me.</note> Where by the way, take notice;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50193:21"/> there is a viſible Salvation on anothers Faith; <hi>Believe thou, and thy Houſe ſhall bt ſaved.</hi> And why the Houſe on his Faith? and how ſaved, but exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, becauſe baptized? And there are many Scriptures to like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> Whereas you tell me, <q rend="inline">That the Reaſon why in the Primitive times, whole Houſes were baptized, is the ſame upon the account of which <hi>Abraham</hi>'s whole Houſe was Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</q> That the reaſon is not the ſame is evident; inaſmuch as Baptiſm did not take place in the manner that Circumciſion did: For Circumciſion was but in one Family, ſingled out from all the Families of the Earth, of the Males only, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Covenant of Grace or no, Children or Servants, elder or younger, at eight days old, by the Maſter of the Family, or others in his ſtead: But in Baptiſm it is clean otherwiſe, and therefore the reaſon of the one cannot be the reaſon of the other. And as to the bringing in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50193:22"/> of whole Families together; it was but contingently ſo, not always ſo, nor conſtantly ſo, according to any Promiſe or Prophecy; and when it did ſo happen, we find not any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant baptized, nor any intimation of baptizing Houſholds in conformity to the adminiſtration of Circumciſion, but rather the contrary; expreſs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice being given, of the Faith and Repentance of thoſe admitted unto Baptiſm, in the ſeveral Houſholds recorded to have been baptized; whereas all were to be circumciſed, that were of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family, both Children, Servants, Slaves and all; whether making a profeſſion of Faith and Repentance or no. And this may appear by taking a view of the ſeveral examples of Baptizing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the New Teſtament; which I have elſewhere ſpread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
               <p>Only at preſent, as to that that concerns the example of <hi>Lydia,</hi> it muſt of neceſſity be underſtood ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the other inſtances, which when they expreſs the baptizing of Houſholds, they expreſs alſo the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving or receiving of the Word by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50193:22"/> the whole Houſhold; and by the frequent uſe of the Word, which is to put the Houſe, for the people of growth in it. As to that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Gaoler; it doth not appear unto me from the Scripture you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor from any other; That there is a viſible Salvation grounded on external holineſs; or that any are ſaved by anothers faith, as you would have it: It being manifeſt by the following Words, That thoſe of the Gaolers Family were ſaved by their <hi>own</hi> Faith, and not by the Faith of <hi>another:</hi> For though <hi>ver.</hi> 31. it was ſaid unto him; <hi>Believe thou on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and thy Houſe;</hi> yet it is expreſly told us, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. <hi>That when he had brought them into his Houſe, he rejoyced, believing in God with</hi> all his Houſe. And that the Salvation here ſpoken of, is not to be underſtood of a <q rend="inline">vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, external Salvation, becauſe baptized (as you expreſs it) is evident:</q> for that this would have been but a poor comfort to the poor trembling Gaoler; of whom it is ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 29, 30. That <hi>he ſprang in and came trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and fell down before Paul and Silas,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50193:23"/> ſaying, <hi>Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> Certainly he was now toucht with a ſenſe of his eternal ſtate: the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply whereunto muſt therefore of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be correſpondent.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">p 55, 56. Thus ran the Drs. firſt Letter to me; thô this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is now ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the printed copy thereof.</note> It ſeems to me to anſwer exactly to the Promiſe given to the Church under the Meſſiah, that magnificent one; for ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 31. it ſhould be rendred, and not in the plural, as we do read it. To the letter, it is not their Nobles, as in our tranſlation, but their magnificent one, or their Noble one ſhall be of themſelves, and their Governour ſhall proceed from the midſt of them. Now the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is, that when this Noble and magnificent one, the Shiloh ſhould come out of the Loins of <hi>Judah,</hi> and take the Soveragn Government and Power, and have the chief admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of things in his own hand: Then in that glorious and Evangelical Diſpenſation, Their Children ſhould be as afore-time: their Children ſhould be ſolemnly dedicated, and given up to God, and put into his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50193:23"/> and in token of it be baptized, as in aforetime they were Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 20, 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> I am not convinced that this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in the 30. of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> hath at all any reference to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and I preſume the true ſenſe and ſcope of it to be miſtaken in your application of it. I acknowledge that all the Promiſes, precedent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent in that context, relate to the happineſs of the Church, in the Kingdom of the Meſſiah, when that Noble and Magnificent one ſhould come, and have the chief adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things in his own hands; amongſt which this is one, <hi>Their Children ſhould be as afore-time.</hi> But what then? doth it therefore follow, that their Infant Seed ſhould be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, in token of their dedication to God, as in afore-time they were Circumciſed? was there ever ſuch an inference drawn from this Text before? Certain it is that there are many hundreds of places in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that might eaſily be alledged,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50193:24"/> wherein <hi>Children</hi> are mentioned, where yet <hi>Infants</hi> cannot be at all intended. And it is as plain, that as for the preſent Words, according to the current expoſition of the place, it muſt needs be underſtood of the body of the Jewiſh Nation, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Scripture called the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and that their being as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, only points back to the moſt proſperous ſtate of that people and particularly to the reigns of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> at which time that Kingdom was at the higheſt exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its proſperity and glory. I deſire you therefore to examine ſuch Expoſitors as you have by you upon the place. I ſuppoſe you are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with more than my ſelf: but I am apt to think, among them all, you will hardly find your own expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 56.</note> Well may the Children in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Diſpenſation be as afore-time; ſince though the Jews are cut off, the Gentiles are graffed in upon the ſame ſtock: not indeed upon the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50193:24"/> legal Branch, but upon the Root Olive, which affordeth all the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment that either the Jews had, or the Gentiles have. Which Root Olive is the Covenant of Promiſe, that was four hundred and thirty years before the Law. Now into that ſtate of things, wherein not the Law, but the Goſpel preached unto <hi>Abraham</hi> did obtain; God was a God not only to the Father, but to the Children: yea to all his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And the Father of the Family did not only give himſelf, but all his Children, and even his Servants, all his to God. And ſo it is now, your Children ſhall be as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> As for the Root mentioned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. to which I ſuppoſe you refer: it is indeed variouſly conceived by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters; ſome underſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Covenant to be meant, ſome <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> and ſome <hi>Abraham</hi> only. For my own part; I believe that Chriſt himſelf is thereby to be underſtood; who is the only
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50193:25"/> Root of the Church; and that both in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time, and before, as well as ſince. To this purpoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tells us, <hi>John</hi> 15. 5. <hi>I am the Vine, ye are the Branches.</hi> And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 16. he ſtiles himſelf, <hi>The Root and the Off-spring of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> It is indeed therefore the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable bleſſedneſs of Gentile Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, to be graffed in upon ſuch a Stock, not upon the legal Branch; but upon the Root Olive; which afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the nouriſhment that either the Jews had, or the Gentiles have. That Root Olive being no other than Chriſt himſelf, who was indeed given for a <hi>Covenant of the people, and a Light to lighten the Gentiles.</hi> The Goſpel of whoſe Grace was (as you ſay) preached to <hi>Abraham</hi> four hundred and thirty years (at leaſt) before the Law was given. But what then? doth it therefore follow that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles are put into that very ſtate of things, as the promiſe held it ſo long before the Law? Where is that Scripture that ſays it? <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. the Scripture before mentioned, ſpeaks no ſuch thing: nor any other that I can meet with.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50193:25"/>
               <p>Evident it is, that though Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was in uſe before as well as under the Law; and though Jeſus Chriſt himſelf is by the Apoſtle ſtiled the Miniſter of the Circumciſion, for the truth of God, to confirm the Promiſes made unto the Fathers; yet as it cannot be denied, but that it was <hi>adopted</hi> into the legal Family; and that it was alſo <hi>adapted</hi> unto the nature and quality of the legal Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: So it is as evident that it is now aboliſhed. And I can meet with no one Text in all the New Teſtament, that tells us that Baptiſm is come in the room thereof; or that it is appointed to have the ſame place and uſe in the Church of God, that Circumciſion had, but rather much to the contrary, as I have elſewhere proved to you: And it being mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the external adminiſtration of the Covenant is now changed, from what it was in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time; from thence it doth as plainly follow, that there is an alteration of the Rule, that muſt direct us in our practice in that reſpect.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:50193:26"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 62, 63.</note> It cannot be denied but that the true ſeed (the believing Gentiles) are as much obliged to keep the Covenant in the ſign of it, both by taking it upon themſelves, and by putting it upon their Children; as <hi>Abraham</hi> was for himſelf and his. And this is the proper duty required of them, as they are partakers of the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Nor are we to expect any New Commands in the Goſpel-Diſpenſation for duties ſetled of old, on laſting and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reaſons; the obligation abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if the reaſon of the precept abides. A principle that is the ground of the Apoſtles Reaſoning, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 8, 9. 10. And ſhall the Principle abide, and not the duty which ariſes from it? the Covenant abide, and not the Reſtipulation, without which it is not a Covenant? This you dare not ſay.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50193:26"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> How fair and ſpecious a ſtructure may there be erected upon a falſe or a wrong Hypotheſis. All this Diſcourſe of yours proceeds from a miſtake in the very foundation of your Argument: For you ſuppoſe, and would fain have it taken for granted, That the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> under the Goſpel, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an obligation from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. to keep the Covenant in <hi>the ſign of it;</hi> and that both by taking it upon <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and by putting it upon their <hi>Children</hi> alſo; whereas there is not a Word or Syllable there, or any where elſe in all the Old Teſtament, That the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> under the Goſpel, were to keep the Covenant <hi>in the ſign of it;</hi> much leſs that they were to <hi>put it upon themſelves;</hi> and leaſt of all, that they were to <hi>put it upon their Children alſo.</hi> All theſe are meer <hi>Inventions,</hi> and <hi>unproved Dictates.</hi> And therefore though we may not expect any New commands in the Goſpel-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for <hi>duties ſetled of old,</hi> on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50193:27"/> laſting and immutable Reaſons; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Obligation abides, if the reaſon of the Precept abides: yet what ſhall we ſay when that which we ſuppoſe or affirm of this kind, is but a meer <hi>Chimera,</hi> or a fancy of our own Brain only? Let it once be ſubſtantially proved, either from the 17th. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> or from any other Text in the Old Teſtament, what you have now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted; and then your conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſhall be as readily grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> I pray conſider, That not only <hi>Abraham</hi> was under Obligation to keep the Covenant in the ſign of it, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo; that is, all thoſe to whom the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is made, are equally obliged to the obſervation thereof <hi>in the ſign of it:</hi> (and therefore) not only <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was obliged, but his Seed too. For as God is pleaſed to ſay; <hi>I will be a God to thee and to thy Seed: and I will give to thee and to thy Seed:</hi> So he ſayes, <hi>Thou and thy Seed ſhall keep</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:50193:27"/> 
                  <hi>my Covenant. Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore;</hi> (and not only thou, but) <hi>thou and thy Seed after thee in their Generations: Thou, thou and thy Seed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that if the Believing Gentiles be (as indeed they be) the true Seed, and principally intended in the Promiſe; (For it is Seed, not Seeds; Seed ſpeaking but of one, and that one is Chriſt; and Chriſt not perſonal only, but myſtical, or Chriſt with his members; for it is of many in one: for the Seed which is to keep the Covenant, is to do it in <hi>their Generations;</hi> not in <hi>his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> but in <hi>their Generations,</hi> and that is plural.) I ſay, if the <hi>Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gentiles</hi> do become the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (as they do) they come alſo under <hi>equal Obligation</hi> to obſerve the Covenant, with <hi>Abraham</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for it is, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant therefore, thou and thy Seed.</hi> And to keep the Covenant (as I have evinced already) is for him that is in it, in token of his dedication, and aſſignment of himſelf, and of all his to God, not only to wear the ſign of the Covenant himſelf in his own
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50193:28"/> perſon, but to put it upon all his that are capable of it; ſo to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that he owns not any intereſt or propriety at all in any thing, or title to any, but what he returns to God; and that both himſelf and all his, are the Lords. And are not the Believing Gentiles as much obliged to aſſign, and dedicate, and give all, as <hi>Abraham?</hi> Yes, doubtleſs, and are as much bound to ſhew, and own, and declare they do ſo, as he.</p>
               <p>And though (as you object) Circumciſion, that at <hi>firſt</hi> was the ſign and token of the Covenant, is taken away; yet it will not follow, that the Obligation to obſerve and keep the Covenant in any <hi>other</hi> ſign or token doth ceaſe with it. And to demonſtrate this, it muſt be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that as the equity and Reaſon of the command doth hold in Baptiſm, as well as in Circumciſion; and for any other ſign and token, as well as for this; and to the Seed as well as to <hi>Abraham;</hi> God being as much a God to the one, as to the other: So alſo that in the form of the Words, the obligation impoſed upon <hi>Abraham</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50193:28"/> his Seed, is in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place, to keep the ſign and token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or to keep the Covenant in the ſign of it. And but in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> (place,) to obſerve circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; namely, but as it is that ſign: So that a plain diſtinction is made between the <hi>Obligation,</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Sign</hi> and <hi>Token</hi> of the Covenant, (or to keep the Covenant in the ſign and token of it) and to keep it in <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> as that Sign and Token; the <hi>Former</hi> ariſing from the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Covenant, <hi>(Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore)</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of as perpetual obligation and exiſtence, as the Covenant it ſelf: But the <hi>Latter</hi> is more poſitive and ſecondary. Wherefore, though there be an alteration in the ſecond, it will not follow that there muſt be one in the Firſt; or that the Covenant ought not to be obſerved in the Sign and token of it, if for certain Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Circumciſion be no longer, but ſomething elſe be that Sign and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; the taking away the <hi>Second,</hi> doth not deſtroy the firſt, for being before it, it may be without it. Thou ſhalt keep the ſign of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50193:29"/> that is firſt; Circumciſion is that Sign, that is Second: And why <hi>one</hi> in the firſt place, and the <hi>other</hi> but in the Second, but to ſhew, the Covenant muſt be kept in the Sign of it, even when no longer Circumciſion, but ſome other thing is in the Counſel of God ordained to be that Sign?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> As to the firſt part of what you now offer; though I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the true Believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, are the Children of the Promiſe. And though I do alſo acknowledge that ſince the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down of the partition-wall by the death of Chriſt, the believing Jews and the believing Gentiles are no more diſtinguiſhed, and of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Seeds, as many, or diverſe; but are made one in Chriſt; yet I deny that the Holy Ghoſt in this Text points at any New Teſtament Sign, with which the Spiritual Seed were to be ſigned in the Goſpel Day; their Obligation to wear the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſign, being wholly left unto the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50193:29"/> time of its Inſtitution; which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines both the ſubjects and the duties thereof. And,</p>
               <p>As for the ſecond part of what you now offer; having diligently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the Scripture which I ſuppoſe you referr to; <hi>viz. Gen.</hi> 17. For my own part, I muſt needs profeſs, I can find no ſuch diſtinction there, as is ſuggeſted by you: for thus run the Words, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>God ſaid unto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou, and thy Seed after thee in their Generations.</hi> Ver. 10. <hi>This is my Covenant, which ye ſhall keep between me and you, and thy Seed after thee; every Man-Child among you ſhall be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</hi> Where I can find no ſuch diſtinction as you obſerve; <q rend="inline">That <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed were enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>firſt</hi> to keep the Covenant <hi>in the ſign of it;</hi> And in the <hi>Second place,</hi> to keep it in Circumciſion, as that ſign.</q> For the immediate Obligation which was laid upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed after him in their Generations, was not to keep the Covenant <hi>in the ſign of it</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral terms, as you would have it; but to keep it in that particular ſign
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50193:30"/> of Circumciſion; there being in that Scripture no other ſign mentioned, or implyed; in which the latter words are only exegetical of the former, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore,</hi> &amp;c. in the 9. Verſe; And how? the 10. Verſe explains, Namely, in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 84. 85.</note> Seeing this Objection hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it very pertinent: (for I will do you all the right imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable) I hold my ſelf obliged in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the removing of it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to the further illuſtrating, and clearing of my Argument, to ſhew, Firſt, That the immediate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, and incumbence mentioned in the 9. Verſe, cannot be to keep the Covenant in, but Circumciſion, or in Circumciſion only. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that what is ſaid, Verſe 10. is not meerly exegetical of the obligation in the 9.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the immediate Obligation, and incumbence in the 9. Verſe, is to keep the Covenant in the ſign of it; this is Primary:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50193:30"/> And then, that which is added in the 10. Verſe, is but a ſecondary inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a particular ſign for that time. And,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I will ſhew, that there is a plain intimation, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more than a meer hint, that ſome other ſign muſt be obſerved by the Seed than that of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> Sir, I muſt needs tell you; That notwithſtanding all the pains you have taken, in your ſecond Letter, toward the proof of the three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, now mentioned by you: you are yet extreamly defective therein.</p>
               <p>For, Firſt, You have told me indeed (to this purpoſe) by way of confirmation of your firſt particular, <q rend="inline">That the immediate Obligation and incumbence mentioned in the 9. Verſe, cannot be to keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in Circumciſion only: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as God promiſeth to be a God unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Seed: So the Spiritual Seed, as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50193:31"/> well as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound to keep the Covenant. And ſince the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> under the Goſpel, are no way obliged unto Circumciſion; ſome other ſign therefore (ſay you) muſt be intended in the Text.</q> But this is not home enough to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for the Argument would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther run thus: That therefore it is the more convincingly evident, that the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> under the Goſpel, are no way concerned in that Obligation; becauſe without giving the leaſt hint of any other ſign: Circumciſion, the only ſign there mentioned, hath relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his natural off-ſpring and family only.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Whereas you tell me, <q rend="inline">That the immediate Obligation and incumbence in the 9. Verſe, is to keep the Covenant, <hi>in the ſign of it;</hi> which you ſay, was <hi>Primary.</hi> And that which is added in the 10. is but a <hi>Secondary</hi> inſtitution of a particular ſign for that time.</q> This being without a ſubſtantial proof, is but a meer <hi>Petitio Principii:</hi> or a plain begging the Point in diſpute, upon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50193:31"/> which the ſtreſs of the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends. For as it is evident that the words in the 10. Verſe, are only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egetical of thoſe in the 9. And as it is evident that neither in the 9. nor in the 10. is there any other ſign men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, but the ſign of Circumciſion only: So it is as evident that the words in the 9. Verſe, do neither <hi>expreſs,</hi> nor give any <hi>intimation</hi> of any ſign at all, that God intended ſhould be annexed to the Covenant, as the token, badge, or cogniſance of it; there being no ſuch term, or a ſyllable of that ſound in the Text: For there God only commands <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to keep his Covenant; and doth not ſay: Thou ſhalt keep it <hi>in the ſign of it:</hi> that being <hi>your addition</hi> only. In the 10. Verſe, indeed we have a particular explanation of what had been delivered in general terms in the 9. <hi>This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep between me and you, and thy Seed after the; every Man-child a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> So that it is apparent that the latter words are only exegetical of the former; and are therefore the <hi>Primary,</hi> and not the <hi>Secondary</hi> Inſtitution of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50193:32"/> a particular ſign, as you would have it.</p>
               <p>And Thirdly, your aſſertion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is groundleſs, when you tell me, <q rend="inline">That there is a plain intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the 9. Verſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more than a meer hint, that ſome other ſign muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Seed than that of Circumciſion:</q> For though the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the Covenant on <hi>Gods part,</hi> doth <hi>now</hi> belong equally to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles, as well as to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Believing off-ſpring <hi>then;</hi> yet as to what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the <hi>Obligation,</hi> there is nothing expreſſed in the whole 17. of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> but what relates to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Natural Seed and Family only. Under the Goſpel indeed, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles are taught what God <hi>now</hi> requires of them, as their duty by way of Reſtipulation: But as this place of <hi>Geneſis</hi> gives no hint at all of Gods mind in that reſpect; ſo neither was there any neceſſity thereof; God only then deſigning to ſignifie unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> together with his natural Seed and Family, what was their preſent duty, under
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50193:32"/> the then preſent Adminiſtration, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>You your ſelf cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Obligation mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 10. Verſe, muſt of neceſſity be underſtood in relation only to the Natural Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> becauſe the Seed there ſpoken of are expreſly enjoyned to be Circumciſed. And if ſo, then it clearly follows, that the general obligation lying upon the Seed, mentioned in the 9. Verſe, muſt be underſtood in the ſame ſenſe alſo: For to ſay that the Spiritual Seed under the Goſpel, muſt be underſtood in the 9. and the Natural Seed only in the 10. is a moſt harſh way of the interpretation of the word of God: it being utterly impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that there ſhould be ſuch a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tranſition from one Seed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without any notice given there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But as this would be to make the Scripture unintelligible to a vulgar Capacity; ſo the Words in both Verſes being but one continued Speech, and the Spirit of God plainly ſpeaking, in both, of one and the ſame ſort of Seed, on whom the Covenant of Circumciſion (as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50193:33"/> 
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> expreſly calls it, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 8.) was then to be impoſed; and there being not the leaſt hint in that whole context, of any other ſign, that God intended ſhould be obſerved in the Goſpel-day: there cannot eaſily be a greater violence offered to the Word of God, than to endeavour to faſten ſuch a ſenſe as you do upon it. But certain it is, God never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to leave his inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to ſuch ambiguous uncertainties, which require ſuch a circumlocution of Words and Arguments, for the demonſtration of them, as you are forced to uſe in the preſent caſe in your ſecond Letter; and which a common capacity cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, when all is done.</p>
               <p>I know you have endeavoured to confirm your expoſition of this Text in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> from the like form of Words in the Fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in relation to the Sabbath: But I ſuppoſe I have given you a ſufficient anſwer to that in my ſecond Letter, which I need not here repeat.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:50193:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">P. 134, 135</note> Conſider ſeriouſly, how plain and eaſie a ſenſe this is I have of the Words (in diſpute) <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me the Lord, and thee <hi>Abrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit, to be a God to thee <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and to thy Seed after thee, <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit. Verſe 8. And I will give to thee <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit, all the Land in which thou art a Stranger. Even the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> in the Letter, to <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter; and the World, the whole World, in the Spirit and Myſtery, to <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the myſtery. Verſe 9. And therefore thou <hi>Abraham</hi> and thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit, ſhall keep (the ſign of) my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Verſe 10. (But) This is (the ſign of) my Covenant which ye which are now here, thou <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> thy Son, according to the fleſh, and the reſt of thy Houſhold here, which ſtand for all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50193:34"/> the Seed according to the fleſh, as ſo; This is (the ſign of) my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye for your part, ſhall keep, (as a ſign of the Covenant I have made between me and ye, and thy Seed <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Seed of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and not of the Fleſh) <hi>Every Man-Child among you</hi> (ye the Natural Family and Carnal Seed) <hi>ſhall be Circumciſed.</hi> Among you, he doth not ſay among the Seed; the Seed is to keep the Covenant in <hi>a</hi> ſign, verſe 9. But the Natural Family only are to keep it in <hi>this</hi> Sign, in Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore,</hi> (in the Sign of it) <hi>thou and thy Seed.</hi> (But) <hi>This is my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man-Child ſhall be Circumciſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> Your Paraphraſe upon the Words is two ways faulty: For firſt it is forced; not natural nor obvious. And Secondly, it is repugnant both to the Text, and to it ſelf. Firſt to the Text, in forcing one Sign upon it, more than it ever intended, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm. Secondly, to it ſelf,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50193:34"/> and the Text too: For if the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed were to keep it in <hi>this</hi> Sign, <hi>viz.</hi> in Circumciſion; and the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Seed in <hi>the</hi> Sign, <hi>viz.</hi> in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; and if <hi>Iſaac</hi> be the Spiritual Seed; then it follows, if <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain only the capacity, and relation of the Spiritual Seed, he ought not to be Circumciſed, which he was: if of the Natural and Spiritual Seed too, (as you make him) he ſhould be both Circumciſed and Baptized alſo, which he was not. Yea, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your reckoning, <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, as well as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſhould have been Baptized: For if the Sign in the 9. Verſe be Baptiſm, as you intimate; the Obligation there, is on <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> too, in the Letter, as well as on the Seed in the Goſpel-day: For thus runs your own Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe upon the Words, <q rend="inline">Therefore thou <hi>Abraham,</hi> and thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit, ſhall keep the Sign of my Covenant.</q> That is, according to <hi>your Senſe;</hi> Both he and they, and thou alſo muſt be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:50193:35"/>
               <p>'Tis true, the <hi>true Senſe</hi> of the Words we all know (or ſhould know at leaſt) is this; <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy Seed,</hi> Verſe 9. That is, <hi>Both thou and thy Seed ſhall be Circumciſed;</hi> as the 10. Verſe declares: And ſo the Words run ſmoothly, without jarring, ſuitable to the plain ſcope of the Spirit of God in the following Words. But according to the courſe that you take, I do not ſee how you can poſſibly avoid the abſurdity; but that the ſenſe muſt be plainly this: Thou, even thou <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhalt be Baptized, as well as Circumciſed; as alſo thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter, together with thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Spirit, (or thy Spiritual Seed in the Goſpel-day) as the proper Sign of that Covenant, which I have now made both with thee and them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Doctor.</label> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 160, 161, 162.</note> It is a bold abuſe you put upon me, when you intimate as my Opinion, That Baptiſm is <hi>immediately intended</hi> in the 9. Verſe. Whereas (you know)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50193:35"/> I have told you ten times over, That I underſtand the keeping of the Covenant there <hi>generally,</hi> for keeping of it in the Sign of it (whatever the Sign at any time be) and not <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly</hi> and <hi>determinately</hi> for keeping of it <hi>immediately</hi> either in Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or in Baptiſm. Indeed in that moment, when the general Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was impoſed of keeping the Sign, neither Baptiſm nor Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>particular was</hi> yet Inſtituted; though Circumciſion was in the very next Moment. I confeſs, had the keeping of the Covenant in the ſign of it, which is the duty enjoyned in the 9. Verſe, been a keeping of it <hi>particularly,</hi> and <hi>determinately</hi> in either Baptiſm, or Circumciſion; then (as you object) either <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt have been <hi>Baptized,</hi> if Baptiſm had been intended particularly; or elſe, <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Spirit (the Believing Gentiles, the true Spiritual Seed) muſt have been Circumciſed, if Circumciſion had immediately and particularly been meant: But that <hi>term</hi> being underſtood but <hi>generally</hi> and <hi>indeterminately; Abraham</hi> and his Seed are only obliged by it to keep
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50193:36"/> the Covenant in <hi>ſome</hi> Sign; in that ſign <hi>reſpectively,</hi> which ſhould be the Sign of their reſpective times: And thus <hi>Abraham</hi> did keep it in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, the ſign in his time; and ſo did <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter, as the Natural Off-ſpring of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the Sign that then was: But Spiritual <hi>Iſaac</hi> (or the Believing Gentiles) could not keep it in the Sign <hi>then;</hi> they not having Being <hi>then,</hi> and ſo no particular Sign was ordained for them <hi>then;</hi> but when ever they ſhould be, They (being the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi>) are tyed by the obligation (Verſe 9.) to keep the Covenant in the Sign of it, <hi>viz.</hi> In that Sign which then ſhould be (the Sign) when they became Seed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Apothecary.</label> In this you ſeem to me to give up your Cauſe for loſt: You now tax me for a bold abuſe, in ſaying, <q rend="inline">That you intimate that Baptiſm is <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately intended</hi> in the 9. Verſe of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</q> Mark your own Word; not <hi>inſtituted</hi> but <hi>intended:</hi> Whence I argue, if Baptiſm be neither there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50193:36"/> 
                  <hi>inſtituted,</hi> nor <hi>intended;</hi> if it be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Letter</hi> nor <hi>Intention</hi> of that Text, it is not there <hi>at all.</hi> And all the noiſe you have made about it, is but a beating of the Air. And whereas you do alſo tell me; the ſenſe is <hi>indeterminate</hi> and <hi>general:</hi> Here you leave me a fair Field; for whether the ſenſe be determinate or no, I appeal to all the rational World to determine; except you will dare to interrupt the Spirit of God in a continued Speech, break the Series of his Diſcourſe, put a ſtop where you pleaſe, before he hath ſpoken out, and catch one part, before the other, which determines the ſenſe, be uttered; and then call it <hi>indeterminate</hi> and <hi>general.</hi> But this is not to be endured among men; you your ſelf would not ſuffer it to be thus handled: much leſs will God ſuffer it. Doth not God in the ſame breath (as I may ſay) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the ſenſe, and tell you where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Covenant is to be kept, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Circumciſion? Do not theſe Words immediately follow the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; <hi>This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Every Man-child among</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:50193:37"/> 
                  <hi>you ſhall be Circumciſed?</hi> And do they not determine the ſenſe? What a liberty do you take, not only to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret this Text, but to rend one part from another, and put Periods where you pleaſe? But why do I beat the Buſh, when the Bird is fled? Baptiſm it ſeems, is neither in the <hi>Letter,</hi> nor <hi>intention</hi> of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. and if ſo, the Diſpute is ended, and we are where we were before. Had there been <hi>a</hi> ſign, or <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. Verſe, diſtinct from that in the 10. the one Baptiſm, the other Circumciſion; <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the ſubject of the latter, as a repreſentative of the Carnal Seed; and <hi>Iſaac</hi> of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as a figure of the Spiritual: (as your former Diſcourſes ran) then <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt have been <hi>Baptized,</hi> or elſe you make him a ſtrange Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. But now you yield, he was neither Baptized in his own perſon, nor Baptiſm ſo much as <hi>intended</hi> in the 9. Verſe: And what more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction can I expect from you? you may diſtinguiſh <hi>the, thou,</hi> and <hi>ye,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>thy Seed after thee,</hi> as ſubtilly as you can.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50193:37"/>
               <p>But though you acknowledg Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is not the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe of Verſe 9. Yet it may be you will tell me, It is the <hi>remote</hi> ſenſe: Yes ſure, <hi>remote</hi> enough, and out of the ken of all men beſide your ſelf. But I pray you, where do you find this <hi>remote ſenſe,</hi> and what is the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe, if neither Circumciſion nor Baptiſm be there? The Covenant it ſeems, according to this reckoning, may be kept without any ſign; which yet you would not allow of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. But pray tell me, How was <hi>Abraham</hi> and his to keep it in the <hi>general, indeterminate</hi> ſenſe, which is neither in the one, or the other ſign? I am afraid this will puzzle you; if not you, it doth ſuch a ſoft head as mine. Did not you tell me in your laſt; The Covenant muſt be kept in ſome ſign; and yet now it may be kept without any? <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy Seed after thee,</hi> that is, <hi>in the ſign of it:</hi> But that muſt not be underſtood, ſay you, in any <hi>particular,</hi> or <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate</hi> ſenſe; but in <hi>general</hi> only: For though Baptiſm is intended, yet it is not <hi>immediately</hi> intended, but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motely</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50193:38"/> only: but you may diſtinguiſh as you pleaſe, Baptiſm, I am ſure, is not to be found in the <hi>expreſs</hi> words of the Text; and you your ſelf do now acknowledge, it is not in the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe; and I have proved that the ſenſe cannot be <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> and <hi>indeterminate.</hi> What need any more ado then to darken counſel thus, by words without knowledge? There ſeemed once <hi>a</hi> ſign, or <hi>the</hi> ſign, in the 9. Verſe, diſtinct from that in the 10. but now it is vaniſht, and there is no ſign there at all, only in a <hi>general, indeterminate,</hi> and <hi>remote</hi> ſenſe, that is, in <hi>no</hi> ſenſe. So that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his, according to your interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, were obliged to keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in a <hi>nonſenſe</hi> way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="notice">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50193:38"/>
               <p>THE Reader is deſired to take notice, that the Doctor never yet gave me any anſwer to this laſt Reply of mine; nor indeed unto many other paſſages of a like impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, contained in my ſixth and laſt Letter to him, (hereafter inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in reference whereunto, he hath been hitherto wholly ſilent. He acknowledgeth indeed in his Preface to the Reader, p. 3. <q rend="inline">That he had received a Letter from me, ſince his laſt:</q> but withal ſays; <q rend="inline">That that Letter (as others) was ſo little to the purpoſe, unleſs reflections and extravagancies be ſo, that he did not find himſelf obliged to any other anſwer, than what in his laſt is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and marked with an Aſteriſm thus*, and that, as himſelf acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, is but little; being (ſaith he) but one Paragraph, and two or three Words by way of illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q> And for that that is, for my own part, I do not ſee how it comes to <hi>bear</hi> upon any part of my laſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50193:39"/> by way of anſwer thereunto. The Doctor indeed tells the Reader, That that Letter of mine is but little to the purpoſe; it may be it is but little to <hi>his</hi> purpoſe, but I hope it is enough to <hi>mine:</hi> But whether it be ſo extravagant, and ſo little to the purpoſe, as the Doctor would have it; or whether he would not have anſwered it, were it not for the knots that are in it, which he could not untie; is now to be referred to the Readers judgment.</p>
               <p>The Doctor tells me indeed, <hi>p.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. in the latter end of his fourth Letter, which that laſt Letter of mine gives anſwer unto: <q rend="inline">That I had treated him but (as <hi>Aeſop</hi> did his Maſters Gueſts) with Tongue, Tongue ſtill, nothing but Tongue in ſeveral diſhes.</q> I hope the Reader will find ſomewhat of <hi>Brain,</hi> as well as <hi>Tongue.</hi> However Tongue is good meat, and many Men much affect it; either when themſelves carve it, and others receive it with admiration; or others carve it, and they receive it, well ſawced with adulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50193:39"/>
               <p>There is one thing more which I judge it needful to give the Reader Advertiſement of; and that is, That that which the Doctor calls his firſt Letter, is to ſpeak truth, no other than two Letters conjoyned in one, or his firſt and ſecond Letters united together: For whereas I had ſent him my ſecond Letter in anſwer to that which was indeed his firſt; by way of reply, he was pleaſed to ſend me back again, almoſt an entire tranſcript of his firſt Letter, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with ſome animadverſions on my anſwer: wherein, himſelf now acknowledgeth in his Preface; That as he thought, I had obliged him to make ſeveral additions and alterations, as well as emendations, by my anſwer thereunto. And this is that which he now calls his firſt Letter, which therefore hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble date. If therefore the Reader find one or two paſſages in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Scheme, which are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be found in that firſt Letter of his, as it is now altered; this which I have now ſaid, will afford a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon for the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50193:40"/>
               <p>And becauſe I thought it might be burthenſome to the Reader to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe all the ſeveral Letters which I have ſent unto the Doctor upon the foregoing ſubject; eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſubſtance of them hath been already preſented in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Scheme: I have therefore only ſubjoyned my two laſt Letters unto him; wherein the main of the Controverſie between us is ſummed up; and though one or two paſſages even in thoſe Letters alſo, have been already recited to make up the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Scheme entire; yet the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity thereof in that reſpect, will I ſuppoſe, render it ſufficiently excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable to the Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">Upon the whole, ſince accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Doctors own conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Baptiſm is not immediately intended in thoſe Words, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. And it being as plain, that it cannot be remotely intended there, and that much leſs can it be found in any other Old Teſtament Text. And for as much as the Doctor hath yet nevertheleſs aſſerted, in the 10. page of his Epiſtle to the Reader;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50193:40"/> That in the New Teſtament no new rule is given by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, or by his Apoſtles and followers, about the ſubjects of Baptiſm: I ſhall now therefore appeal unto the diſcerning Reader, whether the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor muſt not of neceſſity be at a great loſs concerning the grounds of Infants Baptiſm; which yet he tells his Reader, he hath ſo fully aſſerted, and that in a method wholly new, and upon grounds not commonly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Indeed it cannot be denied to be in a method wholly new, and upon grounds not commonly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſince he rejects all other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments as hanging it on Wyres, or by Geometry only. But I am apt to think that whatever the common Arguments will be found to have done, the Doctors new Method (at leaſt) doth ſufficiently appear to have ſo ſerved it: For if there be no rule given for it, either in the Old Teſtament, or in the New; then it hath no foundation in the Word of God at all: And if it hath no foundation there; the Wit of Man cannot acquit an action ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50193:41"/> performed, from the Guilt of Will-Worſhip; and conſequently from hanging it on Wyres, or by Geometry only.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50193:41"/>
               <head>My Fifth Letter to the Doctor.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOurs of <hi>October</hi> 14. hath been thus long before me; being more puzled <hi>how</hi> than <hi>what</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; for I find it eaſier to anſwer what is <hi>Argumentative</hi> in your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, than how to word the juſt <hi>reproofs</hi> I have to lay before you, in ſuch clean, mild, decent, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Language, as may be fully <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive</hi> of my mind, and no way juſtly <hi>offenſive</hi> to yours. Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is called by a great Divine, the Chirurgery of the Paſſions; and cutting work is not eaſie or pleaſant. Here lies then the difficulty of my Province, not to ſtir up your Paſſions, whilſt I am labouring to clear up the truth; that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves me in this point is, that I have to do with a generous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50193:42"/> 
                  <hi>Adverſarius non Perſonae, ſed Litis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> ſharply rebuked one that delivered a Paper to him ſo timorouſly, as if he had been reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſtipem Elephanto,</hi> a morſel to an Elephant; but I hope I may approach you with more freedom with theſe Papers, expecting at leaſt as much humanity, and a great deal more Chriſtianity from you, whilſt I thus Animadvert on yours.</p>
               <p>You tell me, <q rend="inline">My laſt was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to you; becauſe you learn by it, that the Controverſie long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, and which you feared would be eternal, is not like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By way of Reply unto which, Firſt, I give you your word <hi>eternal</hi> back again, as improper, and out of place here: ſure there are no ſuch litigations in eternity. Thoſe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Souls that have entred that ſtate, do not miſtake three for two, and two for one, as we blind mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals do: And Secondly, whereas I perceive you are willing to end the controverſie, the ſooner the better,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50193:42"/> ſay I; ſo you end it fairly by untying, not cutting the knots that are in it. And indeed for my own part, I had rather be ſucking the Marrow of practical Truth, than exerciſing my Teeth always upon the Bones of Controverſie.</p>
               <p>You blame me for applying the phraſes of Plain, Scriptural, Solid, and Cogent, to my own Diſcourſes; and of Chimaeraes, Repugnances, doubtful Conſequences, ambiguous uncertainties, violence and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Scripture (to which you might have added unproved dictates) to yours.</p>
               <p>To which I reply, That if I did not think my own to be Scriptural, ſolid, and cogent; they ſhould be none of mine. And if it do not appear that yours are as I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, I will beg your pardon: But I doubt you have given too much ground in theſe, as well as your former Papers, to juſtifie thoſe Cenſures.</p>
               <p>You put the whole Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie upon theſe two Iſſues, <hi>viz.</hi> the Duty enjoyned, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 17. 9.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50193:43"/> and the ſubjects of that duty, Verſe 10.</p>
               <p>Candidly and fairly offered (ſay I) I do accept therefore and joyn Iſſue with you, upon this reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſtulatum, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bible may be Judge, for I pretend to no knowledg in the <hi>Hebrew;</hi> as alſo that you do not wreſt or cloud the genuine ſenſe by artifice or elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For one of the Antients pertinently obſerves; <q rend="inline">That the ſtate and condition of the moſt perſpicuous truth is often obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and altered, according to the ſtrength or eloquence of thoſe that diſpute it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay, That you have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly evinced that by <hi>Seed</hi> in the 9. Verſe, muſt be underſtood the Spiritual, as well as the Carnal Seed.</p>
               <p>To this I reply, That that may be eaſily evinced which was never controverted. I grant you that the Spiritual Seed, <hi>viz. Iſaac</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the 9. Verſe, but that which you are to prove, is that <hi>Iſaac, quatenus,</hi> or <hi>as</hi> the Spiritual
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50193:43"/> Seed is there meant; I ſay this is what reſts on you to prove; elſe you only ſay, but not diſpute, and will juſtifie me in calling your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes unproved Dictates; I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect I ſay, ſolid proof for this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a foundation ſtone (ſuch as it is) in your ſtructure; but I doubt this will never be proved by you. I am ſure not from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which you palpably abuſe, by miſrendring it; In <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall <hi>the Seed</hi> be called; the Text ſaith not ſo, but <hi>thy Seed.</hi> And the Apoſtle alledging it twice in the New Teſtament faith, <hi>thy Seed,</hi> not <hi>the Seed,</hi> as you do, which had you done by way of expoſition only, it had been the more excuſable; but an allegation is one thing, and an expoſition is another. And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant that when we cite a Scripture, we ought to cite it in the ſame ſyllables, and be preciſe to a point; foraſmuch as on every point of the Law Mountains of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hang. Now though it is true that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a type of Chriſt, and ſo, of the Believing Gentiles alſo;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50193:44"/> 
                  <hi>Iſaac</hi> being born after the Spirit, as a Child of the Promiſe; and not barely after the fleſh as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was; yet I deny that <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (that is, the Believing Gentiles) is at all to be underſtood by the Seed expreſſed in the 9. Verſe, becauſe the Seed there mentioned, is commanded in the 10. to be Circumciſed; which doth not at all ſuit with the believing Gentiles; but muſt of neceſſity be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural poſterity by <hi>Iſaac</hi> only.</p>
               <p>Nor indeed was it under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe notion, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed, that the preſent obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was at all faſtened upon him (there being nothing of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentioned throughout the whole context) but rather as he was deſcended from <hi>Abraham</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Iſhmael</hi> had been excluded from the duty there mentioned, who could pretend to nothing of any Spiritual Relation unto <hi>Abraham</hi> as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did; And yet it cannot be denied but <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50193:44"/> therein as well as <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our buſineſs is to ſhew who were to be Circumciſed, and in what Capacity, Reſpect, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, you are coming to that; and in order to it, in the next place, you aſſert a tripartite Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> God on the one part: <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Natural Family denoted by the Word <hi>ye,</hi> on the ſecond part: And <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit, and in him the believing Gentiles, denoted by the Seed, on the third part.</p>
               <p>You asked me before, How I durſt diſtinguiſh where God doth not? I do not know that I did; but I think you do ſo here. And ſhould I ſay no more but, <hi>turpe eſt Doctori,</hi> &amp;c. it may be I had ſaid enough to that: But I pray you, dear Sir, How prove you this Covenant to be tripartite, which ſeems to be bipartite only; by Verſe 2. and Verſe 4. only <hi>Abraham</hi> is conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it as <hi>Pater Familias,</hi> and his off ſpring both preſent and future taken in with him, as one party in the Covenant; even as <hi>Noah</hi>'s Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50193:45"/> is expreſſed in the ſame form, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 9. I know not what Authorities you follow, I wiſh you would be ſo juſt to your ſelf, to produce them in your own vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for I think you tread a very ſolitary and By-Path here. But by the ſame Rule and Reaſon you make it a tripartite Covenant, you may make it quadrupartite if you pleaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> God is one party, <hi>Abraham</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, his preſent Family a third, and his Seed after him a fourth: But when a Mans Eyes are once dazled, nothing is more common than to ſee three for two, and two for one, as you here do: three Parties and two Signs, which is the next thing.</p>
               <p>For you make two diſtinct Signs as well as three Parties in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: And that I may not abuſe you; I will ſet down <hi>verbatim,</hi> your own Paraphraſe upon the Words; which though you call plain and eaſie, it is to me the moſt involved, tortuous, and intricate, that ever I heard of, except <hi>Origens Allegorical,</hi> and <hi>Myſtical Commentaries:</hi> But
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50193:45"/> ſuch as it is, I ſhall here ſet it down, and my own by it, that all may judge which flows moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus runs your Paraphraſe; ſpeaking of the 9. Verſe, ſay you:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Therefore thou</hi> Abraham, <hi>and thy Seed</hi> Iſaac, in the Letter and Spirit; <hi>ſhall keep</hi> (<hi>the</hi> ſign of) <hi>my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
                  </q> And then ſpeaking of the 10. Verſe, you bring in that Verſe with a <hi>But,</hi> thus: <q rend="inline">(But) <hi>this is</hi> (the ſign of) <hi>my Covenant which ye</hi> which are now here, thou <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> thy Son, according to the fleſh, and the reſt of thy houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here, which ſtand for all the Seed according to the fleſh as ſo; <hi>This is</hi> (the ſign of) <hi>my Covenant which ye</hi> (for your part) <hi>ſhall keep</hi> as a ſign of the Covenant which I have made <hi>between me and ye, and thy Seed</hi> Iſaac, the Seed of the Promiſe, and not of the Fleſh; <hi>Every Man-child among ye,</hi> ye the Natural Family, and Carnal Seed <hi>ſhall be Circumciſed;</hi> among ye,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50193:46"/> he doth not ſay among the Seed. The Seed is to keep the Covenant in a ſign, Verſe 9. But the natural Family only are to keep it in <hi>this</hi> ſign of Circumciſion. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore</hi> (in the ſign of it) <hi>thou and thy Seed:</hi> (but) <hi>this is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Every Man-child ſhall be Circumciſed.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>My Paraphraſe.</label> I enter into Covenant with thee <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with thine; in which Covenant I confer upon thee and them, all ſorts of Bleſſings, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal; Temporal upon thy Natural Seed, and Spiritual and Temporal on thy Spiritual Seed. And by way of reſtipulation, I require, That both thou in thy own perſon, and they in theirs, both thoſe that are preſent and future, keep my Covenant: And becauſe thou mayeſt underſtand what I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of you; this is my Covenant, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the ſign of it to thee and them in their Generation, which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50193:46"/> thou and they ſhall keep; <hi>Every Male among you ſhall be Circumciſed.</hi> This is the plain and obvious ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Your Paraphraſe is two wayes faulty: For firſt it is forced, not natural, nor obvious. And Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is repugnant both to the Text and to it ſelf. Firſt to the Text, in forcing one ſign upon it more than it ever intended, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm. Secondly, to it ſelf and the Text too: For if the Natural Seed were to keep it in <hi>this</hi> ſign, <hi>viz.</hi> in Circumciſion, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed in <hi>the</hi> ſign, <hi>viz.</hi> in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> be the Spiritual Seed; then it follows, if <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſuſtain only the capacity and relation of the Spiritual Seed, he ought not to be Circumciſed, which he was; if of the Natural and Spiritual Seed too, (as you make him) he ſhould be both Circumciſed and Baptized alſo, which he was not. Yea according to your reckoning, <hi>Abraham</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as well as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſhould have been Baptized: For if the ſign in the 9. Verſe, be Baptiſm, as you
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50193:47"/> intimate; the obligation there is on <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> too; as well as on the Seed in the Goſpel-day: For thus runs your own Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe upon the Words, <q rend="inline">Therefore thou <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>thy</hi> Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Letter and Spirit ſhall keep the ſign of my Covenant,</q> that is, both <hi>he</hi> and <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> alſo, muſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               <p>It is true, the true ſenſe of the Words, we all know (or ſhould know at leaſt) is this; <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy Seed:</hi> That is, both thou and they ſhall be Circumciſed; as the 10. Verſe declares: And ſo the Words run ſmooth, without jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſuitable to the plain ſcope of the Spirit of God in the following words: But according to the courſe that you take, I do not ſee for my own part, how you can poſſibly avoid the abſurdity, but that the ſenſe muſt be plainly this; Thou, even thou <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhalt be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; as alſo thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the <hi>Letter,</hi> together with thy Seed <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> (or thy Spiritual
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50193:47"/> Seed in the Goſpel-day,) as the proper ſign of that Covenant, which I have now made both with thee and them.</p>
               <p>But I muſt a little further mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt what I but now hinted alſo, concerning your forcing one ſign upon the Text, more than it ever intended, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm; which is indeed the foundation of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going abſurdity: For you tell me of <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. Verſe. And <hi>this</hi> ſign in the 10. <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. Verſe, relating, ſay you, to the Believing Gentiles: And <hi>this</hi> ſign in the 10. to the natural poſterity of <hi>Abraham:</hi> But pray hold there, Sir, we muſt not be put off ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For as far as I can diſcern, God ſpeaks but of one ſign in both Verſes. I acknowledge, as you ſay, <q rend="inline">That the ſenſe and meaning of the Phraſe of keeping the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in either Verſe, is clearly the meaning of it alſo in both. And therefore to keep the Covenant in the 9. Verſe, is to keep the ſign of the Covenant, ſeeing to keep the Covenant in the 10. Verſe, is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50193:48"/> to keep it in the ſign;</q> but then we muſt not make two ſigns, where God ſpeaks but of one. It cannot be rationally denied (as your ſelf do now ſeem to grant) but that the words in the 10. Verſe, are only exegetical of thoſe in the 9. and then where are the two ſigns you ſpeak of? No, Sir, we can allow of no Rules of Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Multiplication, at this rate, when we come to interpret the Word of God; for that is, as I have already told you, highly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. It is true, twice one makes two; <hi>a</hi> ſign or <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. and <hi>this</hi> ſign in the 10. that is, a ſign of Gods appointment in the 10. and another of your own deviſing in the 9. But certainly this kind of courſe will not do, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake by this time, I ſuppoſe, is diſcernable enough; only I muſt tell you, that as far as I can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, it was your over earlineſs in giving the ſenſe of the 9. Verſe, that hath led you into the preſent error; for had you waited Gods leiſure, and tarried till God himſelf
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50193:48"/> had ſpoken, as he doth in the 10. Verſe, by way of explication of thoſe general words in the 9. you had not run into that fatal miſtake as now you do, of making two ſigns where God makes but one; and conſequently of adding a ſign of your own, to that of Gods appointment.</p>
               <p>As I take it, one of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſaith, That if the Workmans Hand were his Rule, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver err in working. And if what you pleaſe to paraphraſe on a Text, muſt be the ſenſe, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fail to carry any cauſe you undertake: for after this rate a man of an ordinary capacity may undertake to prove <hi>Quidlibet à Quolibet;</hi> what himſelf pleaſes from any Text whatſoever. But really Sir, this is not to interpret, but to wreſt the Scriptures. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. that is, To put them on the rack to force them to ſpeak what they never meant. <note n="*" place="margin">To which I may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly add, what the Wiſe man ſaith, Prov. 30. 5. 6.</note> You will bear with my plainneſs herein, the merit of the cauſe lies in it; and your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to force the Scriptures, as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50193:49"/> you do, is no ſmall evil. Thus Sir, your <hi>foundation</hi> fails, and <hi>debile fundamentum fallit opus:</hi> All the reſt you have ſo artificially ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, totters of courſe. I ſhall now therefore animadvert upon only one word more in your Paraphraſe, (though more might be ſpoken to) and ſo proceed to anſwer the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Queſtions you propound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me;</p>
               <p>And that is the Word, <hi>But;</hi> in reſpect of which I pray you to tell me by what Authority we ſhall be aſſured, that the words in the 10. Verſe, are indeed to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted disjunctively, as you do ſuggeſt, while you begin that verſe with a <hi>But,</hi> as you do in your Paraphraſe thereon? <hi>(but)</hi> ſay you, this is the ſign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas there is no ſuch Word in the Text, nor any thing like it that I can meet with. Indeed you could never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to carry the cauſe you plead for, but by the addition of this disjunctive word, <hi>But,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the 10. Verſe, where there was none before: For thus run
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50193:49"/> the Words in their naked ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, according to the commonly received Tranſlation of them. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy Seed,</hi> &amp;c. Verſe 9. And then Verſe 10. <hi>This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. But you have thought fit to add this Word, <hi>But,</hi> in the beginning of the 10. Verſe, to make it run the more plauſibly to your own ſenſe (which it would not do without) whereby you would inſinuate as if God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected his ſpeech to another ſort of perſons there than in the 9. and indeed if that word had been added by the unerring Spirit of God, the words in both Verſes, would clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough have had quite another ſenſe, than now they have: But as the caſe ſtands, that word muſt be expunged; for as far as I can ſee, there is no reaſon why it ſhould be put in: God doth not ſay ſo; and therefore why ſhould you.</p>
               <p>And now Sir, having run through your Paraphraſe, I come to the Queſtions you propounded, which
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50193:50"/> are grounded thereupon. In my Anſwer whereunto, I muſt have an eye to your Paraphraſe, becauſe I find the one is made to fortifie and give life unto the other. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I ſhall reſpect both in my Anſwers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Quer. 1.</label> And Firſt, you demand, Is there not a Word, not a ſyllable, as you expreſs it (ſay you) in the 17. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> are to keep the Covenant in the ſign of it?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> I Anſwer, That this Phraſe, <hi>the ſign,</hi> is equivocal. According to you, it is Baptiſm; according to my ſenſe, and the plain Scripture, it is Circumciſion. That <hi>Iſaac</hi> and all believers of the Old Teſtament, lineally deſcending from <hi>Abraham,</hi> were obliged to keep the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Circumciſion, the declared and determinate ſign of it, I grant. That there is any other ſign, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that in this 17. Chapter, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and you have not offered the leaſt proof for it, beſides your own Paraphraſe upon the Words; which is to dictate, not to diſpute.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:50193:50"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu. 2.</label> You demand; Have not I prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Seed there is <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Spirit principally?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> If by <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Spirit you mean the believing Gentiles; I Anſwer, No: but I have rather proved the contrary; to wit, that the Seed there mentioned is to be underſtood of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Poſterity by <hi>Iſaac</hi> only. And the reaſon is plain, becauſe the Seed mentioned in the 9. Verſe, are expreſly command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 10. to be Circumciſed; which doth not at all relate unto the Believing Gentiles, but muſt of neceſſity be underſtood of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Natural Poſterity on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>That the Holy Ghoſt under the New Teſtament makes <hi>Iſaac</hi> a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt, and of them that are born after the Spirit, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not. But that <hi>Abraham</hi> as well as <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> ſhould in this place ſtand for the Carnal Seed, and <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> for the Spiritual Seed only; as your Queſtion implies, and your Paraphraſe expreſſes; and that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſhmael,</hi> and the reſt of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:50193:51"/> preſent Family, as ſtanding for the Carnal Seed, ſhould be here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinguiſhed to <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the keeping of this Covenant in the ſign of it; is what you have not, and I preſume never will be able to prove. This Phraſe <hi>the Seed,</hi> as it ſtands in your Queſtion, would indeed intimate ſuch a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; <hi>the Seed</hi> being an empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical expreſſion; but there is no ſuch word in the Text, as <hi>the Seed;</hi> however you have adventured to put it in, as more ſitting your turn, than thoſe Words the Holy Ghoſt was pleaſed to uſe in this 9. Verſe, <hi>thy Seed.</hi> The Text puts them in conjunction in the ſame Promiſe and Obligation; you in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and accordingly alter the Phraſe, to ground your notion upon it: But did <hi>Abraham</hi> in the buſineſs of Circumciſion ſtand indeed for the Carnal Seed, as you ſay, as well as <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> How then did he receive Circumciſion as a Seal of the righteouſneſs of Faith?</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:50193:51"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu. 3.</label> Doth not God, ſay you, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>ye</hi> and <hi>the Seed?</hi> And is not Circumciſion enjoyned only on the Natural, Carnal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the term <hi>ye,</hi> as it is diſtinguiſhed from <hi>the Seed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> No, there is no ſuch diſtinction, but of your own making. The terms of every diſtinction muſt be oppoſite, elſe it is no diſtinction; but here they are conjoyned as one party in the Obligation. And <hi>the Seed</hi> which you would make one member of the diſtinction, is a ſelf created term, as I have told you upon the former Queſtion. It is <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thy Seed</hi> after thee in the 9. Verſe, pointing not only at <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but at all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s poſterity in their reſpective Generations, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the continuance of that Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. And then it follows in the 10. Verſe, <hi>This is my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. meaning <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed after him in their Generations, which had been ſpoken of juſt before; ſo that God doth not diſtinguiſh between
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50193:52"/> 
                  <hi>ye</hi> and <hi>the Seed;</hi> as you ſay he doth: Nor doth it appear that Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is enjoyned only on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, Carnal Family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the term <hi>ye,</hi> as it is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from <hi>the Seed;</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obj.</label> But then you do alſo tell me, That the ſubject of the Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Circumciſion in particular, which is in the 10. Verſe, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, it is not there, ſay you, <hi>Thou and thy Seed,</hi> as all along be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but <hi>ye,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> is <hi>Abraham,</hi> and thoſe then with him in the Letter: But <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not there, who was the promiſed Seed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> Could Gods mind, I pray you, be more fitly expreſſed in the ſenſe I have pleaded for, than to ſay, <hi>This is my Covenant which</hi> ye <hi>ſhall keep,</hi> in the 10. Verſe, meaning <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed after him, ſpoken of in the 9. It is true, the Words <hi>thee</hi> or <hi>thou</hi> are not to be found in the 10. Verſe, nor was it fit they ſhould; for it would have been altogether improper to have ſaid in the 10. Verſe, <hi>This</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:50193:52"/> 
                  <hi>is my Covenant which</hi> thou <hi>ſhalt keep between me and you,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe God intended that his Covenant ſhould be kept by more than one; even by the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, as well as by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> himſelf: And therefore it is moſt fitly expreſſed as it is, in purſuance of the ſenſe I have pleaded for, <hi>This is my Covenant which</hi> ye <hi>ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And whereas you tell me, That <hi>ye</hi> is <hi>Abraham,</hi> and thoſe then with him in the Letter; but <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not there, who was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Seed. What do you drive at in this expreſſion? would you have me believe, as your words do ſeem to import, that <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Promiſed Seed was not to be Circumciſed, becauſe he was not there when the command of that kind was given to <hi>Abraham</hi> and the reſt then preſent with him in the Letter? It is true, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not then preſent with him, as being not yet born; but yet he was as much comprehended in the term <hi>ye,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf; for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50193:53"/> in the 9. Verſe, concerned the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> as much as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf; and therefore ſo doth the term <hi>ye</hi> in the 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu. 4.</label> Again, (ſay you) Why doth God diſtinguiſh the <hi>ye,</hi> from <hi>the Seed [between me and ye and thy Seed]</hi> by which I ſuppoſe you mean thoſe words in the latter part of the 10. Verſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> I anſwer, That as far as appears to me, God doth not diſtinguiſh the <hi>ye</hi> from <hi>the Seed,</hi> except as one was preſent, the other future; but both together making one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Covenant. <hi>This is my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which ye ſhall keep between me and you, and thy Seed after thee,</hi> &amp;c. For I have already proved, that <hi>ye,</hi> in the beginning of this Verſe, muſt of neceſſity comprehend all thoſe that had been before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the foregoing Verſe; that is, <hi>Abraham and his Seed after him in their Generations:</hi> But then whereas God ſaith; <hi>This is my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye ſhall keep</hi> between me and you: This can be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in my opinion, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:50193:53"/> than thus, <hi>Between me and you;</hi> that is, Between me, and thou <hi>Abraham,</hi> together with thy Son <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and the reſt of the Family now preſent with thee: and not only between me and you now preſent; but <hi>between me and you, and thy ſeed after thee,</hi> before expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; <hi>Every Man-child among you ſhall be Circumciſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu. 5.</label> In fine, (ſay you) why all along in the 10. and 11. Verſes, and afterward both in the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Circumciſion, and in the intimation of the end and uſe of it, doth the Holy Ghoſt uſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive term, and never mentions <hi>the Seed; but ye, ye ſhall keep it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And it ſhall be a token between me and ye;</hi> he ſaith not, <hi>the Seed ſhall keep it,</hi> &amp;c. nor, <hi>That it ſhall be a token to the Seed.</hi> He ſayes, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Seed ſhall keep the Covenant [in <hi>a</hi> ſign]</hi> but doth not ſay, <hi>it ſhall keep the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in <hi>this</hi> ſign; it ſhall keep</hi> a <hi>ſign,</hi> not this <hi>ſign;</hi> And why ſo? clear up theſe Queſtions (ſay you) and you do ſomething; and without it all is nothing.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:50193:54"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> The reaſon then (ſay I) Why in the beginning of the 10. Verſe, and afterward, both in the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Circumciſion, and in the intimation of the end and uſe of it, the Holy Ghoſt doth uſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive term; is, becauſe it would have been improper ſo often to have repeated the word <hi>Seed,</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the uſual forms of ſpeech generally in cuſtome among men) it being enough when <hi>Abraham and his Seed after him,</hi> had been once or twice mentioned, to ſay <hi>ye,</hi> as there was further occaſion to make mention of them; he needed not afterward to ſay, <hi>The Seed ſhould keep,</hi> &amp;c. Nor that it ſhould be a token to <hi>the Seed: But</hi> ye <hi>ſhall keep it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And it ſhall be a token to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whereas you tell me, That God ſays, <hi>the Seed ſhall keep the Covenant,</hi> [in <hi>a</hi> Sign] But doth not ſay, <hi>it ſhall keep the Covenant in</hi> this <hi>ſign; it ſhall keep</hi> a <hi>ſign, not</hi> this <hi>ſign,</hi> And why ſo?</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:50193:54"/>
               <p>I anſwer, That God doth not ſay, <hi>That Abraham or his Seed ſhould keep the Covenant [in <hi>a</hi> ſign]</hi> nor in <hi>this</hi> ſign; nor indeed in <hi>any ſign</hi> diſtinct from that which is expreſly mentioned in the 10. Verſe. <hi>viz. The ſign of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion;</hi> for that is the only ſign ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, or ſo much as hinted at, in that whole Chapter: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for you to make two ſigns where God ſpeaks but of one, as I have already told you, is no ſmall tranſgreſſion. The ground of which miſtake, ſeems to have been your over haſtineſs in giving the ſenſe of the 9. Verſe, before the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon; whereas you ſhould have waited till God himſelf had ſpoken, as he doth to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the following words; but by this means (your interpretation and Gods being put together, though yours was needleſs while Gods was in place) on a ſudden up ſtarts the appearance of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incumbence, where but one was intended.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Qu. 6.</label> Laſtly, you demand, Is not the ſame the ſubject in the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50193:55"/> in the 9. Verſe, that is, in the promiſe Spiritual in the 7. and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in the 8.?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sol.</label> Yes, and the ſame that is in the 10. alſo; that is, <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his, whether preſent or future, Carnal, or Spiritual, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ſome way or other. In the Bleſſings temporal, the Carnal Seed were concerned. In the Bleſſings Spiritual and Temporal, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. And both the one and the other were alſo concerned in the Obligation mentioned Verſe 9. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to be <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> as the 10. Verſe declares. And it is plain that <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> as well as <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> the Believing Jews as well as the Carnal, were conſtantly Circumciſed; and not one to keep it in one ſign, and another in another, as you ſuggeſt without any ground from this Text.</p>
               <p>But to leave as little matter as may be for further ventilation; though I do acknowledg that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a figure of thoſe born after the Spirit: And that the Believing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50193:55"/> Gentiles, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, are the Children of the Promiſe. And though I do alſo acknowledge that ſince the taking down of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Wall by the death of Chriſt, the believing Jews and the believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gentiles are no more diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and of different Seeds, as many, or diverſe, but are made one in Chriſt: Yet I deny that the Holy Ghoſt in this Text points at any New Teſtament ſign, with which the Spiritual Seed were to be ſigned in the Goſpel-day: their obligation to wear the Goſpel ſign, being wholly left unto the time of its inſtitution; which deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines both the ſubjects and duties thereof.</p>
               <p>And therefore though it cannot be denyed, but that <hi>Abraham,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Covenant with God himſelf, was expreſly commanded not only to wear the ſign of it himſelf; but to put it upon his Children alſo: And not only ſo, but on his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Slaves and all; yet you can produce no command to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe under the Goſpel in reſpect of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50193:56"/> Baptiſm. I know very well this is the point you drive at: But as you have yet produced no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture proof for the maintenance of your aſſertion of this kind, but <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. ſo I have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that thoſe words concern the Natural poſterity of <hi>Abraham</hi> only. And though <hi>Abraham</hi>'s being in Covenant was a ſufficient ground for him at the command of God to put the ſign of it upon his off ſpring alſo; whether believers or no: Yet it is expreſly required that the perſons to be Baptized be Believers themſelves; for thus runs the Goſpel Commiſſion, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>He that believeth and is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>If thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou mayeſt,</hi> &amp;c. Which qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not required of thoſe to be Circumciſed, as the condition thereof, whether of Infants or thoſe at Age; ſo that now it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſay as the Jews did in <hi>John</hi>'s time; <hi>We have Abraham to our Father:</hi> But thoſe to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, muſt make (at leaſt) a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50193:56"/> of Faith and Repentance, themſelves, before they can be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admitted thereunto. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Baptize Infants that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of either, is no other than to croſs the Goſpel Rule. And I could never yet meet with two Rules in reference to Baptiſm, one relating to Infants, and another to thoſe of Age; but that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the adult only; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently unto ſuch alone as are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the terms which the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel now requires.</p>
               <p>And indeed, if it were granted that the believing Gentiles are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as the proper ſubject of the Obligation, mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. Yet you cannot from thoſe Words ſubſtantially prove that the Infant Seed of Believers are to be Baptized with their Parents: For there God only ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy Seed after thee in their Generations:</hi> And that is all. There is no mention in that Text, of putting the ſign on their Children alſo, as was the caſe in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time. It is true
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50193:57"/> by the Seed there ſpoken of you underſtand the Spiritual Seed in the Goſpel-day; and by keeping the Covenant you underſtand their keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in the proper ſign of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Goſpel, that is, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: but where lies the ground for Infant Baptiſm in all this? For if we exempt <hi>Abraham</hi> as not being at all concerned in the Goſpel Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which you ſay is there intended; and allow that it hath relation only to the Spiritual Seed in the Goſpel-day; let thoſe then that are ſuch, when they deſire it, be Baptized: But is there a word or ſyllable there concerning the <hi>Infant Seed</hi> of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that they alſo muſt be Baptized? Or muſt we forge a commiſſion out of our own Brain to this purpoſe, where the Scripture it ſelf is ſilent? Let the Spiritual Seed then keep the Covenant in the proper ſign of it in their own perſons; and when you can produce any teſtimony from the Scriptures, that, becauſe Believers themſelves are in Covenant, their Infants muſt now be ſigned alſo; I hope we ſhall not ſail to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:50193:57"/> to the Divine Precept. But for you to pretend to a plain, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, Scripture proof for Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm from the words inſiſted on; as far as I can ſee, while the World ſtands, you will never be able to make good what you would pretend unto upon that account.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſtated the Iſſues on which the thing in controverſy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us now depends; and having anſwered your Queſtions, I hope I may alſo take the boldneſs to ſay, That I have done it with the candor and fairneſs that becomes a ſeeker of truth; and ſhall therefore ſtill beg of God to lead both you and me into the way of all truth, that the remaining darkneſs on your mind or on mine, in our preſent ſearches after it, may at length be diſpelled. Thus reſteth,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Yours in all Chriſtian Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Affection, <hi>Philip Cary.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>Dartm. <date>Dec. 15. 1682.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:50193:58"/>
               <head>My Sixth and laſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was never yet anſwered.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I find your laſt of a different complexion and ſtile from your former; abounding with ſarcaſms, Jeers, and opprobrious terms; and all ſtrangely connected with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of candor, lenity, and ſoft Words, and that you dare not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your ſelf ſuch a liberty as I take in this kind. At this I am aſtoniſhed, and provoke you to ſhew one opprobrious term appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your perſon in all my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. Your perſon I honour, when I cenſure and detect your
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50193:58"/> miſtakes. But I ſee it is time to turn the Cask upon its Head, when its come to the Bottom, and runs ſo foul and dreggy. I know no uſe of ſcoffs in Controverſie, but to diſtract an Adverſary, and fill up the defects of ſound Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>I perceive you are very angry with me for telling you; That when a mans Eyes are once dazled, nothing is more common than to ſee three for two, and two for one, as you do; but I hope you will readily grant that it is incident to the wiſeſt man on earth at ſome turns to have his Eyes dazled, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a misjudgment and miſapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion both of things and perſons. And I hope you do not reckon your ſelf the only infallible man in the World, but that it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible even for you to have your Eyes dazled ſometimes as well as others. And therefore unleſs you reckon your ſelf above the reach of humane imperfections, I ſee no juſt reaſon you have to be offended at ſuch a reflection as that was.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:50193:59"/>
               <p>I have indeed in divers other paſſages of my laſt Letter, uſed a Chriſtian freedom with you, which ſeems greatly to ſtartle you; but if you will be offended at a ſerious, Chriſtian reprehenſion, becauſe it is of a cutting nature, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. I cannot help that; and therefore though you condemn it as Butcher-like, I ſhall more willingly bear the unjuſt imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a cenſure, than be really guilty thereof, as you ſeem to be in yours. But you could not give a more convincing evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the weakneſs of the cauſe you are ingaged in, than by being forced to fly unto the uſe of ſuch kind of Weapons for the defence thereof; certainly ſofter Words, and harder Arguments would have been more proper for you.</p>
               <p>Your Anſwer I have conſidered both in the whole, and in its parts. In the whole it ſeems to me, one great impertinence; repeating what had been anſwered before; and ſliding by the ſubſtantial part of my former and latter Anſwers; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50193:59"/> only upon ſome by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions (which yet I am ready to vindicate) as fit ſubjects for your pleaſant fancy to expoſe me to contempt and laughter. But this ſtirs no other paſſion in me but pity toward you, that herein act beneath your ſelf: and I would have it leave no other effect or impreſſion on me, but humility; who am all that you call me, and much more; and deſire to be vile in my own Eyes before the Lord, though I have not deſerved this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from you.</p>
               <p>But to the parts of your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: You begin it with a collation of my Papers of the 29. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and my laſt; and fancy that at firſt glance you have found a contradiction in them. Upon which ſuppoſal you ſet your foot upon me, and thus inſult; who is it now that is dazled?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Reply.</label> Your ſelf ſtill (ſay I) for you fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to ſee what is not in theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. I had ſaid in the former; That the Text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no ſign at all, or gives the leaſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:50193:60"/> hint of any: and ſo I ſay ſtill, there is no ſuch term, or a ſyllable of that ſound in the Text: but ſay you, in mine of the 15. of <hi>December,</hi> I acknowledge one ſign: True, I do ſo, as included in the ſenſe, though not expreſſed in the terms. And ſo doth <hi>Junius</hi> in his Note upon that place, <hi>Foedus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymicè pro foederis Symbolo.</hi> And if in this you find a contradiction, your triumph hath ſome footing, elſe all the mirth is marred, and my modeſty ſalved. I am where I was: no ſign mentioned at all in the 9. Verſe, and but one that is or can be allowed in the ſenſe of that whole context.</p>
               <p>As for my ſlipperineſs in your next Paragraph, and a ſoft place in my Head; it is well my ſoft head can find a fair way for me to ſlip from betwixt your fingers, when you thought you had caught me in a contradiction, and inſulted ſo loudly in that conceit. But, Sir, you may ſooner find two ſoft pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in my Head, than two ſigns in that context.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:50193:60"/>
               <p>Your triumph being ended upon that; you preſently find another as bad as the former, ſetting my two papers a ſcuffling again, about another contradiction. For, ſay you, in my former Paper, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the Spiritual Seed, Chriſt and the believing Gentiles; but in this, the perſon of <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> Who that ſhall read my laſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, would think that ever you had read what here you undertake to anſwer? Sir, you abuſe me in this, by a miſrepreſentation of my plain Words and Senſe: For I tell you in my laſt, that I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a Figure of thoſe born after the Spirit; and that the believing Gentiles as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, are the Children of the Promiſe. Had this been heeded, all the pains you take in your firſt page, to evince <hi>Iſaac</hi> to be a figure of the Spiritual Seed, might have been ſpared; for it is what I have plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged; though it be nothing to your advantage; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you could have proved your two ſigns; and that <hi>Iſaac</hi> in <hi>the</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:50193:61"/> ſign, was a repreſentative of the Gentile believers, who therefore with all theirs muſt be baptized, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was. All that deſerves to be remarqued further in your firſt page, is, that grave and worthy note, with which you cloſe it, and for which I thank you. <q rend="inline">That to ſtart a ſenſe of the Spiritual Seed which was not thought of before, is doubling. And a Hare is uſed to double when near run down.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> Your Note is weighty, and the Hare you hunt is not ſo near run down, but that ſhe will double once more; and double your own words upon you too: Have not you ſtarted a new ſenſe of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. which was never thought of by any Father or Commentator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; no Author ever going in your track, but purely novel? And is not this according to your own obſervation, doubling? Really Sir, you convince me, that harder and ſteadier Heads than mine, may now and then nod and forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:50193:61"/>
               <p>But from fiſhing for more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, you fall in the next place, <q rend="inline">a lamenting your misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in having to do with ſuch an Adverſary, who being prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in adherence to an opinion long ago conceived, is obliged to do all things to maintain it; with ſuch a one as is not ſuſceptible of light; yea with ſuch a one as being prepoſſeſſed, winds and turns, and wriggles, and will not admit of plain ſenſe. In a word, one that will not ſee that thrice one makes three. That is neither conſiſtent with himſelf, or his principles, a <hi>Proteus,</hi> a capering <hi>Will with a Wiſp,</hi> an <hi>ignis fatuus;</hi>
                  </q> which in effect is no other than a ſoft-headed Fool. And all this vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out at one guſh, by a man that in the very next words, wipes his Mouth, and profeſſeth he dare not allow himſelf ſuch a liberty as I do; that holds it undecent, and unchriſtian to ſharpen his Pen; and calls him a Butcher rather than a Chirurgeon that delights in cutting, and tearing, and ſlaſhing, when
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:50193:62"/> there is no need of it; that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends ſoft Words and hard Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; when mean while ſoft Words are as great a rarity as hard Arguments, in all theſe your Papers, except theſe be ſuch.</p>
               <p>But what need you ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail your misfortune? though I am not an Adverſary conſiderable enough for you to raiſe your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon; yet I am one of your own chuſing and provoking; and the ſofter and ſimpler you find me, the eaſier will your victory and triumph over me be; only perhaps you reckon it inglorious to enter the liſts with ſuch a contemptible thing as I am.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>No generous Eagle ſtoopeth from on high,</l>
                  <l>To truſs a <hi>Titmouſe,</hi> or a <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-fly.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus <hi>Goliah</hi> deſpiſed that poor Stripling that came againſt him with a ſtaff, and a ſtone. An Elephant ſcorns to fight a Mouſe; yet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Story tells us the event of the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50193:62"/> one, and Prophane Hiſtory of the other; which I ſpeak not in a way of boaſting, but to let you know that you do not well thus to hector me with ſuch kind of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as you do.</p>
               <p>In your next Paragraph you fall ſeverely upon me, for noting your fault in corrupting the Text, by changing <hi>thy Seed</hi> for <hi>the Seed:</hi> the latter being more emphatical, and fit for your purpoſe. In your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence whereof it is very obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able how you twiſt, wind, and turn (to apply your own Phraſes); for firſt you charge it as a miſtake in your Scribe; but after it had been denyed, then charged as an errour in the Scribe: Leſt you ſhould ſeem to err, you undertake the defence of the before acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged miſtake, with a <hi>Quod ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, ſcripſi.</hi> But is this becoming the candor and ingenuity of your character? Who is it now Sir, that is obliged to do all things to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Opinion? to ſay and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, deny, and defend the ſame things? We need not <hi>Argus</hi>'s hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:50193:63"/> Eyes; ſo dull a fellow as I am, diſcerns this ſhuffling with half an Eye.</p>
               <p>And though this courſe be bad in you, and the worſe becauſe you before condemned it (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly in me) yet the <hi>medium</hi> you have choſen to defend that altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text, is a greater crime than to let it paſs as the Scribe's miſtake: for you tell me that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did thus in an hundred places. A ſorry help at a dead lift! How hard is the caſe now with you, that you are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſuch a ſhift as this? Chriſt and his Apoſtles were infallible; are you ſo too? Every variation they made was Authentick, and Canonical Scripture; are yours ſo too? Dare you compare? If you have equal authority, we know where to find an infallible Judge of all controverſies on Earth, near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er home than <hi>Rome:</hi> though I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>John Duns (Scotus)</hi> never heard of any beſides him that wears the Triple Crown.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:50193:63"/>
               <p>But to our buſineſs, ſay you (it is time to come to the buſineſs, ſay I, for all this while you have been beſide it): and thereforenow I expect ſoft Words and hard Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. I therefore diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your next Paragraph, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſay the main of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie lieth. Here you make uſe of my conceſſion; That the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual as well as the Carnal Seed, <hi>Iſaac</hi> as well as <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in thoſe Verſes in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> It is true they were ſo; both the one and the other were to be Circumciſed; but not <hi>quatenus</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: but as the Seed, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſcendents of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But this ſay you is a <hi>Bull:</hi> if ſo, you had need beware, for Bulls have Horns, and will puſh; and ſo will this. For,</p>
               <p>If the proper ſubjects of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion were the Spiritual Seed, <hi>quatenus</hi> Spiritual; then none but the Spiritual Seed ought to be Circumciſed; whereas <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and thouſands more that were not the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:50193:64"/> Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> were; and ought to be Circumciſed.</p>
               <p>But ſay you, though <hi>Iſaac</hi> was Circumciſed, and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> too; yet there are two ſigns in that Text, Circumciſion and Baptiſm. And therefore though <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was to be Circumciſed, as the Natural off-ſpring of <hi>Abraham;</hi> yet <hi>Iſaac</hi> (ſay you) was both in the Promiſe and in the <hi>Obligation</hi> too, to be conſidered as he <hi>repreſents</hi> the Believing Gentiles, the true Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Seed. And thus alſo runs your Paraphraſe upon the words, as it is expreſſed in your former Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <q rend="inline">This is the ſign of my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which ye for your part ſhall keep; as a ſign of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant I have made between me and you, and thy Seed <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Seed of the Promiſe and not of the Fleſh; <hi>Every Man-child among ye,</hi> ye the natural Family and Carnal Seed, ſhall be Circumciſed. <hi>Among ye;</hi> he doth not ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Seed. The Seed is to keep the Covenant in <hi>a</hi> ſign, Verſe 9. But the Natural Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:50193:64"/> only are to keep it in <hi>this</hi> ſign of Circumciſion.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> What pity is it that no man in the World ſhould be able to ſee this beſides your ſelf? I before ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>Iſaac</hi> to be a type, or figure of the Believing Gentiles; but not in Baptiſm, but in the way and manner of his ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral birth, to which our regeneration in ſome ſort correſponds; as you well expound to this purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 13, 16, 17. but that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſign as Baptiſm in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. And that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was ſigned by it as a Type or Figure of the Gentile Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers (as you now ſeem to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and your Paraphraſe imports) I deny, and never expect with all your Art and Sophiſtry to ſee evinced. And indeed you make him a ſtrange Type of the Gentile Believers in point of Baptiſm, if he himſelf were not Baptized, nor ſuch an Ordnance as Baptiſm, at that time inſtituted; he was a type of that which neither was, in it ſelf, nor paſſed upon him. As to any conceſſions of mine, you have
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:50193:65"/> your liberty to make what uſe you pleaſe of them. If I have by inadvertency dropt any word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to this ſenſe (as I know not that I have) evince it, and my recantation ſhall be your ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. In ſumm; I own <hi>Iſaac</hi> to be a type of the Believing Gentiles in the point of the ſupernatural birth. I deny him to be ſo in the point of Baptiſm; and deſire you among all the types in Scripture to ſhew one like this you plead for, that he ſhould repreſent us in the Ordnance of Baptiſm, when he himſelf was never Baptized, nor ſuch an Ordnance in being for many hundred years after his death.</p>
               <p>But whereas you tell me, <q rend="inline">That you have mentioned a conceſſion of mine in a former Letter, and leſt I ſhould either forget it, or ſhould by ſome <hi>evaſion</hi> which you cannot think of, <hi>elevate</hi> the force of it, and ſo create you new trouble hereafter;</q> you will cite the paſſage now, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:50193:65"/>
               <p>To this I reply, That the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage you now cite, being as little to your purpoſe as the former; I ſhall only therefore tell you; That I ſtudy no evaſions to <hi>elevate</hi> the force of what I have ſaid; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that word was the fault of your Scribe too: But for all that you may juſtifie it for ought I know; but if you mean <hi>elude,</hi> I muſt ſay, I need no evaſions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>elude</hi> the force of my own conceſſions, or to <hi>elevate</hi> the force of yours.</p>
               <p>And now, ſay you, it is time to tell you what Authors I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, they are Scriptural ones, ſuch as <hi>Paul, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> There are few errors in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, but pretend to Scripture Authority. Sir, our buſineſs now is the Expoſition of a Text. And <hi>Paul</hi> never told you of two ſigns and three parties in that Covenant. If he doth, I deſire you to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him for it, and he ſhall be more to me than a thouſand Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities: I ſay, ſhew me that Text where <hi>Paul</hi> tells you of two ſigns
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:50193:66"/> in that Covenant; the one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the other Circumciſion; or that <hi>Abraham</hi> was to repreſent the Carnal Seed, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Spiritual. <hi>Paul</hi> I have read, and <hi>Peter</hi> too; but whence your notion is, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell. I think he was as much a ſtranger to it as I and all others, both Antient and Moderns, were, before you were pleaſed to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the world with this new light.</p>
               <p>You come again, p. 5. with your pinching and amazing diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as you call it, of <hi>ye</hi> and <hi>the Seed,</hi> to make the Covenant tripartite.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> I thought I had ſaid enough to that before; that thoſe terms do diſtinguiſh the preſent and future Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but not as two diſtinct parties in the Covenant, but as different perſons; both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but one party, though ſome were preſent, others future. For this you upbraid me, and ſay this is to affirm and deny the ſame thing. But how can you ſay or think ſo? And why do you abuſe your ſelf as well as me in ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming?
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:50193:66"/> Good Sir, uſe your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ingenuity to better purpoſe. May not many perſons, though ſome be preſent, others abſent, be all one party in Covenant, without a contradiction? Let <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. from the 10. to the 16. decide that.</p>
               <p>But for this and no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, you judge my head to be unſetled. If ſo, it is well for me, I am in an able Doctors hand, you have skill, and I have Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore; but bleſſed be God there is no need for either yet.</p>
               <p>From one abſurdity you ſtrive to run me into another, deriding me for affirming that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a diſtinction ought to be oppoſite.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> What ſhall I now do? I am no Academick, but a poor, ſilly, Countrey fellow, and in the hands of a learned Doctor, at whoſe Feet I ſhould rather ſit, than dare to diſpute a Point of Logick. This you ſay is <hi>new;</hi> a <hi>new light;</hi> but that I hope will not offend you; your whole notion being ſo, a new
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:50193:67"/> light altogether, your Expoſition of <hi>Geneſis</hi> 17. being ſuch as no man before you, ever made on that Text. But though that were anſwer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough <hi>ad hominem;</hi> it will not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie me who cenſure you for <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty.</hi> This put me to my ſhifts, and made me inquiſitive after ſome Syſtems of Logick; and I have found two, if they be of any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with you, <hi>viz. Stierius, Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3. who ſaith, <hi>Omnia membra dividentia debent inter ſeſe pugnare.</hi> Are fighters oppoſites? And Doctor <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Compend. Log. p.</hi> 68. <hi>Membra condividentia ſint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtincta, &amp; oppoſita.</hi> But you tell me, My Head, Tongue, and Hand, are diſtinct but not oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. True, in themſelves they are not; but if once brought into a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, I think they would. Should I ask you, did you write your Letter to me with your Tongue or Hand? And you Anſwer not with my Tongue but with my Hand; I think they would be put in oppoſition. But away with this prattle; I am out of my faculty,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:50193:67"/> and will not in this conteſt with you. What is a Dunce to a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor?</p>
               <p>Your next Diſcourſe is to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe; fain would you eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh your tripartite Covenant; and therefore ſhew me firſt a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwixt God and <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was bipartite; then comes in his Seed with him, and this muſt needs make it tripartite.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Rep.</label> There was a Covenant betwixt God the Father and Chriſt; and after that a Covenant taking in all his Seed, called the Covenant of Grace; doth that make it tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite? Are not Chriſt and Believers conſidered but as one Party? This notion vaniſhing, all your over ſubtle diſtinctions of <hi>thou,</hi> and <hi>ye,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>thy Seed,</hi> vaniſh with it. I muſt ſtill ſay you are ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and I hope too modeſt to think that Wiſdom was born with you. I have told you in what ſenſe I allow a diſtinction betwixt <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael, Iſaac,</hi> and all that were to come; they were diſtinct perſons, but one party
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:50193:68"/> in Covenant, and all to be ſigned with Circumciſion. And you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture far without guide or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in affirming <hi>Abraham</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent only the Carnal Seed: for Believers are as often called <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Children, as <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s. I ſay, all theſe forementioned terms ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie no more but <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his, whether preſent or future, as one party with him; and it is not my notion but yours that makes the Scripture unintelligible: For both <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> were <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed, and both obliged to be Circumciſed. And though <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the manner of his birth was the figure or repreſentative of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed; yet this makes not him a third party no more than it did <hi>Abraham</hi> whoſe Children the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed are as often called as they are <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>Your next Paragraph is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſeems to me the giving up of your cauſe for loſt. You there tax me for a bold abuſe, in ſaying, <q rend="inline">That you intimate that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is immediately <hi>intended</hi> in the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:50193:68"/> 9. Verſe of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</q> Mark your own word; not <hi>inſtituted</hi> but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</hi> Whence I argue; If Baptiſm be neither there inſtituted, nor intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; if it be neither in the Letter, nor <hi>intention</hi> of that Text; it is not there <hi>at all.</hi> And all the noiſe you have made about it, is but a beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Air. And whereas you do alſo tell me, the ſenſe is <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate</hi> and <hi>general.</hi> Here you leave me a fair Field: for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſenſe be determinate or no. I appeal to all the rational World to determine: except you will dare to interrupt the Spirit of God in a continued Speech, break the ſeries of his Diſcourſe, put a ſtop where you pleaſe, before he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out; and catch one part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other which determines the ſenſe be uttered; (as I told you in my laſt) and then call it indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and general. But this is not to be endured among men; you your ſelf would not ſuffer it to be thus handled. Much leſs will God ſuffer it. Doth not God in the ſame breath, (as I may ſay) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:50193:69"/> the ſenſe, and tell you wherein the Covenant is to be kept; namely in <hi>Circumciſion?</hi> Do not theſe Words immediately follow the former, <hi>This is my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Every Man-child among ye ſhall be Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed?</hi> And do they not determine the ſenſe? What a liberty do you take not only to interpret this Text, but rend one part from another, and put periods where you pleaſe? But why do I beat the buſh, when the Bird is fled? Baptiſm it ſeems, is neither in the Letter, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9. And if ſo, the Diſpute is ended; and we are where we were before. Had there been <hi>a</hi> ſign, or <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. Verſe, diſtinct from that in the 10. the one Baptiſm, the other Circumciſion; <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the ſubject of the latter, as a repreſentative of the Carnal Seed; and <hi>Iſaac</hi> of the former, as a figure of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: (as your former Diſcourſes ran) then <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt have been Baptized; or elſe you make him a ſtrange Figure. But now you
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:50193:69"/> yield, he was neither Baptized in his own perſon, nor Baptiſm ſo much as <hi>intended</hi> in the 9. Verſe. And what more ſatisfaction can I expect from you? you may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the <hi>thou,</hi> and <hi>ye,</hi> and <hi>you, and thy Seed after thee,</hi> as ſubtilly as you can.</p>
               <p>But though you acknowledge Baptiſm is not the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe of Verſe 9. Yet it may be you will tell me, it is the <hi>remote</hi> ſenſe. Yes ſure, remote enough, and out of the ken of all men beſides your ſelf. But I pray you, Where do you find this <hi>remote</hi> ſenſe, and what is the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe, if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumciſion nor Baptiſm be there? The Covenant it ſeems ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this reckoning, may be kept without any ſign; which yet you would not allow in your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Papers. But pray tell me, How was <hi>Abraham</hi> and his to keep it in the <hi>general indeterminate</hi> ſenſe, which is neither in the one or the other ſign? I am afraid this will puzle you, if not you, it doth ſuch a ſoft Head as mine. Did not you
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:50193:70"/> tell me in your laſt; The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant muſt be kept in <hi>ſome ſign;</hi> and yet here it may be kept <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any? Thou ſhalt keep my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant therefore, thou and thy Seed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee,</hi> that is <hi>in the ſign of it:</hi> But that muſt not be underſtood, ſay you, in any <hi>particular</hi> or <hi>determinate</hi> ſenſe, but <hi>in general</hi> only: for though Baptiſm is <hi>intended;</hi> yet it is not <hi>immediately</hi> intended, but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motely</hi> only. But you may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh as you pleaſe; Baptiſm, I am ſure, is not to be found in the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of the Text, and you your ſelf do now acknowledg, it is not in the <hi>immediate</hi> ſenſe; and I have proved that the ſenſe cannot be <hi>general,</hi> and <hi>indeterminate:</hi> what need any more ado then to darken Counſel thus, by Words without knowledge? there ſeemed once <hi>a</hi> ſign, or <hi>the</hi> ſign in the 9. Verſe, diſtinct from that in the 10. but now it is vaniſht, and there is no ſign there at all, only in a <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, indeterminate,</hi> and <hi>remote ſenſe,</hi> that is in <hi>no</hi> ſenſe. So that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his, according to your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:50193:70"/> were obliged to keep the Covenant in a <hi>nonſenſe</hi> way.</p>
               <p>Your next Paragraph runs you into as bad a ſlough as the former. You ſay you thought to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt the point; but that ſomething came into your mind. It had been well you had kept to your firſt intention, and have let that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of mine that came to your mind, alone, as you have done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others. You had aſſerted that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtood for the Carnal Seed. It ſeems I had objected, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>That he received Circumciſion as a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith;</hi> and therefore ſtood for the Spiritual Seed as well as <hi>Iſaac.</hi> This pinches, and to clear your ſelf to this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome objection, you return two things: Firſt, That the reward was perſonal, and earthly: for ſo is the ſenſe of what you ſay. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That it was given him <hi>for</hi> his believing of the Promiſe to him (ſo improbable, ſo unlikely, and in nature ſo impoſſible) <hi>viz. That he ſhould have Seed as the Stars.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:50193:71"/>
               <p>Sir, I am almoſt as much amaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at your Expoſition of <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. as at that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. Did <hi>Abraham</hi> repreſent none in this, or only the Carnal Seed. And was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward only the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and that reward too <hi>for</hi> his believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing ſo improbable? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will not men run when left to the guidance of their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Fancy? Look again I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you on the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. Was it not that he might be the Father of all them that <hi>believe?</hi> And are all them that <hi>believe,</hi> the <hi>Carnal Seed,</hi> for whom he ſtood? And is it not added, Verſe 23. <hi>That it was not written for his ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone</hi> (as you interpret, and can do no other, if you make him ſtand only for the Carnal Seed) <hi>but for us alſo?</hi> And was the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> the only reward of his Faith? or did he not look for another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 10. And was this reward given him <hi>for</hi> his believing a thing ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and in nature ſo impoſſible? your meaning may be good, but
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:50193:71"/> your expreſſions ſound harſh, and diſſonant to <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. the reward not being of Debt but of Grace; not for the <hi>dignity,</hi> or the <hi>Act</hi> of his Faith, but from Grace.</p>
               <p>All that follows to the cloſe, is a meer ſtrife about Words formerly cenſured by me, and induſtriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindicated by you, with ſome new marks of Reproach with which you brand me: And finding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it but that which you nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeate, and call a brabling bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, I paſs it over, being loth to give you more <hi>Tongue</hi> than needs muſt.</p>
               <p>You ſhut up with a challenge of a Perſonal Diſpute at <hi>Totnes;</hi> and a Menace of printing your part; leaving me to do with mine as I pleaſe.</p>
               <p>As to your Challenge, I dare not anſwer it; not only becauſe I acknowledg you much my ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, and to wear a long Sword, compared with my Dagger. I am as you have repreſented me, and much more; you a man of renown. And therefore if you offer my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:50193:72"/> as a Victim to your glory, it will not be thereby much illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but beſides, the Law allows no ſuch Meetings; and I and my Friends are ſecluſe, and incapable of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing on ſuch a ſcore. I perceive you are well acquainted with <hi>Aeſop's Fables;</hi> I therefore recommend to you, that of the Rat and the Frog at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to go over the Water in conjunction. As it fared with them, ſo it may with us in ſuch a congreſs.</p>
               <p>As for publiſhing your Arguments I cannot oppoſe you; but in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice I think you are bound to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh all mine with them; elſe you will be
<q>In vacuo ſolus Seſſor Plauſor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Theatro.</q> Triumphing and applauding all alone, no Adverſary being with you on the Stage, which is an eaſie tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I think the World will be but little enlightned by ſuch a Diſcourſe of yours, publiſhed in your own vindication. Sure I am,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:50193:72"/> neither the Argument you mannage, or the Adverſary you have choſen, can add one Grain to your Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But do as you pleaſe, and I will do what I ought, and as far as I can, to vindicate Truth; retaining ſtill that Honour which is due to your Perſon and Parts from,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  <signed>Your Affectionate Friend and Servant <hi>Philip Cary.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>Dartm. <date>Jan. 19. 1682.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
